你一个师爷敢冒充县长？
You dare to impersonate the Governor?
那就要看你的本事了
That's all up to you.
师爷，当夫妻最要紧的是什么？
What's important for a couple?
恩爱！
In love.
听不见，再说一遍
I can't hear you.
恩爱！
In love.
来，见过母亲大人
Six, come greet your Mom.
母亲大人好，小六子有礼了！
I wish you well, Mother.
你出生入死，还带着儿子啊？
You bring your son to battles?
他爹是我的兄弟，阵亡了
His father was a comrade. Died in battle.
所以他就成了我的儿子
So I adopted him as my god son.
所以呢，你现在就是我的母亲大人！
Now you're my mother.
等这桩买卖做完后
After we're done with Goose Town,
“天之涯”
"To the end of horizon,"
“地之角”
"four corners of Earth,"
“知交半零落”
"scattered one's true friends"
“一壶浊酒尽余欢”
"A bottle of wine for remaining joy,"
“夕阳山外山”
"as sun sets among the mountains."
好，好好
Brilliant...
汤师爷
Counselor!
是好吃，还是好听？
You prefer the food or my singing?
也好听，也好吃
I love them both!
都好，都好！
Outstanding!
我马某走南闯北
Brain and brawn have helped me far,
靠的就是能文能武，与众不同
that's why I am so unique!
不光吃喝玩乐，更要雪月风花
One must learn to live in style!
马县长此番风度
Governor, with your style and poise,
正好比
you remind me of...
大风起兮云飞扬
a modern-day Robin Hood!
屁！
Bullshit!
刘邦是个小人！
Robin Hood is a common thief!
力拔山兮气盖世
with Samson's might and Solomon's wisdom!
屁！ 屁，屁
- Bullshit! - Yes, bullshit!
汤师爷
Counselor,
你要是拍我马屁
if you're trying to flatter me,
就先要先过夫人这一关
you must first woo my wife!
写首诗，写首诗！
Compose a poem in her honour.
要有风，要有肉
It must have a tempest, food,
要有火锅，要有雾
a hotpot, some mist,
要有美女，要有驴！
pretty maidens, and a mule!
起来，起来，起来
Get up!
一起吃！一起唱！
Let's eat, sing and be merry!
报告县长！我们铁血十八星陆军
Sir, we are the elite Republican Guards,
护送县长安全上任！
here to ensure your safe passage!
我们…
We -
不吃饭！
don't - need - to - eat!
没打中？
You missed?
让子弹飞一会儿
Let the bullets fly...
老二老三跟我走
Two and Three come with me.
其他人把白马抓回来！
The rest round up the horses.
火锅？
Raining hot pot?
爹，全都找遍了
Pop, we've looked all over.
没钱，没货，也没有银子
There is absolutely nothing!
人倒是剩两活的，杀不杀？
Should we just kill the two survivors?
钱藏在哪儿了？说出来
Tell me where the money is?
闹钟响之前要是说不出来
Or I'll cut off your head,
脑袋搬家
when the alarm goes off.
哭？
Stop it!
哭也算时间啊
Tears won't stop it from ticking.
有什么就说什么嘛
You'd better come clean with them.
这位夫人，你是谁？
Who might you be, ma'am?
我就是县长夫人啊
I'm the Governor's wife.
失敬！失敬！
Forgive my impudence.
那你就是县太爷？
So you must be the Governor.
有钱！有钱…！
Yes, of course! There's money!
我跟县长进城上任
We're on our way to inauguration.
县长淹死了，现在没有
He ruined it all by getting drowned!
上任就有！上任就有钱
But we can still hit jackpot
上任就有！
if we take his vacant post.
再给你一圈，顺着买官往下说
I'll give you another chance. Tell me more.
有二十万
$200,000...
钱呢？ 买官了
- Where is it? - Bought the post with it.
他，他县长赚过六百四十万！
That's what the "Governor" made.
我不是师爷么，我就赚个零头！
I only get the small change.
没失过手？
Ever failed?
不动手，拼的是脑子，不流血
We use our brains, not brawn.
你这次去哪儿上任？
Where are you heading to?
鹅城
Goose Town.
火车被劫，你的人淹死了怎么交代？
How do you explain the hold-up and the bodies?
车是我买的，人是我雇的，没人追查
I bought the train and hired the soldiers.
没有人追查
No one will ever find out.
别摘！别摘…！千万别摘！
Don't take it off! Leave your mask on!
规矩我懂
I know the rules.
看见你的脸我就活不成
No one lives after seeing a bandit's face.
你把我放了，我上任鹅城
Just wait here for me.
赚了钱，都给你！都给你！
I'll bring you the money once I have it.
弟兄们劫回道
We came to rob a train,
一分钱都没捞着，不合适吧
we can't go empty-handed.
不合适
No, you can't.
你看了我一眼小命就丢了，也不合适吧
If you die for peeking at me...
更不合适
That's even worse.
你那些淹死的兄弟给我用用？
Can I borrow those bodies?
用！…他们欺男霸女，死有余辜
Yes. These bullies deserve no better.
不是，死了有什么用啊？
But what do you want to do with them?
死人有时候比活人有用
They can be more useful than the living.
师爷，睁开眼看我一眼
Take a look at me.
看一眼
Look at me!
你逃过一次
You've escaped once.
你要是再敢耍我…
Try this one more time...
明白！脑袋搬家
You'll have me beheaded!
进城
Let's go!
城里的女人就是白啊
City girls are so fair and delicate!
"Wanted, Dead or Alive!"
爹，你看
Pop, look!
他们怎么把你画成这样了！
Look what they've made of you!
越不像越安全
The less it resembles me, the safer I am!
恭迎县长大人！
Welcome, your honour!
委任状！
Appointment Warrant!
兹委任马邦德为鹅县县长
Ma Bangde is appointed Goose Town Governor
此状，中华民国萨南康省主席巴青泰
by authority of the Provincial Chairman,
中华民国八年八月二十八日
on this 28th day of February, the 8th year of the Republic...
黄老爷驾到
Master Huang has arrived!
黄老爷吉祥！
Greetings to Master Huang!
Good fortune to Master Huang!
此乃南国一霸黄四郎
Huang Silang is the local godfather.
干的是贩卖人口，倒卖烟土的大生意
Made his fortune from opium and human trafficking.
黄老爷百忙无暇
Master is currently engaged.
特命我黄府大管家胡万！
So he sends his majordomo, Hu Wan!
黄府团练教头武智冲！
And his militia coach, Wu Zhichong!
礼帽，礼貌，欢迎县长！
To welcome you, sir, with his hat!
来者不善啊
Who dares win!
你才是来者
Do you dare?
老爷，来了
He's here, sir.
谁呀？
Who's here?
你自己
Yourself!
黄大爷万寿！
Long live Master Huang!
小的杨万楼，这厢有礼
Greetings from Yang Wanlou!
膺品是个好东西！
A remarkable fake!
走几步
Take a few steps.
走出个虎虎生风
Walk purposefully.
走个虎虎生风
Purposefully...
走出一个一日千里
Walk with spirit.
走个一日千里
Spiritedly...
走出一个恍如隔世
Walk pensively.
走个恍如隔世
Pensively...
买官干什么？ 赚钱
- What for? - To make more money.
能赚多少？ 一倍
- How much? - Twice as much.
多长时间？ 一年
- How long will it take? - A year.
我要等你一年？
I've to wait one year?
半年半年！手气好，一个月也行！
A month, if you're in luck.
县长淹死了，谁去上任？ 我
- Who will be the governor? - Me.
你是谁？ 师爷
- And who might you be? - I'm a counselor.
磕不磕？
Do it!
打！
Flog him!
这个不好使
That's no good.
得使这个！
This is more effective.
哎！别打！我磕！
Stop! I'll do it.
行了
Splendid!
那上面印着他名字的时候
If his name was printed there.
爹，这叫穆扎这人
Pop, this Mozart...
他是怎么把这东西吹到这里边的？
How did he get the sound in there?
你去留完洋，你就什么都知道了
You'll learn by studying abroad.
若是夫人有任何要求
But if you have that urge,
兄弟我…
then yours truly,
也决不推辞
would be happy to oblige.
睡觉
Let's sleep!
一日夫妻百日恩呐
Husband and wife - even for a day...
反正呢，我就想当县长夫人
I've always wanted to be a governor's wife,
谁是县长，我无所谓！
and I don't care who the governor is.
兄弟，别客气嘛
So, brother, be my guest!
我客气吗？
Your guest?
客气呀
Go ahead!
这还算客气？
You make me blush!
你太客气啦
Well, do I?
怎么才能不客气啊？
Then I must oblige.
晚了！
We're late!
前几任县长
Previous governors
把鹅城的税，收到九十年以后了
have levied tax for the next 90 years!
也就是西历二零一零年！
So everyone has paid up to 2010!
咱们来错地方了
We've come to the wrong place!
我倒是觉得这个地方不错
I like this town, though.
百姓成穷鬼了，没油水可榨了
But people here have nothing left.
老子从来就没想刮穷鬼的钱
I never take from the poor.
那你要这么说
If you want to put it that way...
买官当县长还真就是跪着要饭的
Many would love to be in your position,
就这，多少人想跪还没这门路呢！
but few could afford to buy a post.
我问问你，我为什么要上山当土匪？
Do you know why I became an outlaw?
我就是腿脚不方便，跪不下去！
It's because my legs are not built for kneeling!
原来你是想站着赚钱啊！
If you want to make money standing tall,
那还是回山里吧
ride back to the mountains.
这我就不明白了
I don't get this.
我已经当了县长了
I am now governor,
怎么还不如个土匪呀？
how can I be worse off than a bandit?
百姓眼里，你是县长
You may be a governor to the townsfolk.
可是黄四郎眼里
But in the eyes of Huang,
你就是跪着要饭的
you're a mere beggar!
赚钱嘛，生意，不寒酸！
This is only business. There is no shame.
寒酸！
The hell there isn't!
很寒酸
It's shameful!
那你是想站着？
Do you prefer to stand tall,
还是想赚钱呢？
or do you want to make money?
我是想站着，还把钱赚了
I want to do both.
赚不成！
No way.
赚不成？
Why not?
赚不成！
It's impossible.
这个能不能赚钱？
Can I make money with this?
能赚，山里
Yes, but only as a bandit.
这个能不能赚钱？
Or with this?
能赚，跪着
Yes, but only on your knees.
这个加上这个
Combining the two,
能不能站着把钱赚了？
can I make money standing tall?
敢问九筒大哥何方神圣？
Mr. Nine, who exactly are you?
鄙人，张麻子！
"Pocky" Zhang!
那不是树，别砍了！
Stop it! This is not a tree!
这是冤鼓，干隆那时候设的
It's an ancient magisterial drum!
老没人敲就生了根，长了叶
Totally neglected,
没人认识县长长什么模样
They've never met him.
你干过几次？ 一年两次
- Done this before? - Twice a year.
干过几年？ 八年
- Since when? - Eight years ago.
八八六十四，你赚过六百四十万？
You've made more than $6.4 million?
就看一眼
Just one look!
师爷贵姓？ 别客气
- What's your name? - I...
姓什么？ 姓汤
- What's your bloody name? - Tang.
汤师爷，我当县长
I'll be the Governor,
你继续当我的师爷
and you'll be my counselor!
咱们鹅城走一趟
Let's go and rule Goose Town.
夫人，要不要走一趟？
Ma'am, coming with us?
走就走嘛
Well, why not?
嘿嘿嘿，弟兄们上任鹅城
Brothers, let's move on to Goose Town!
上任鹅城！
Goose Town here we come!
兄弟们失了手
We've messed up badly.
让你丈夫横遭了不测
End up drowning your husband.
我很是愧疚
I feel bad about it.
我已经第四次当寡妇了
I've already been widowed four times.
那可千万别第五次哦！
Don't let there be a fifth time, then!
当惯了县长
After serving as county governor,
再回去当麻匪
I can't return to banditry.
恐怕会有点不习’惯吧
I won't be able to handle it.
曾经沧海难为水嘛
Once you've scaled Mount Everest...
说得好
Such eloquence!
那怎么办啊？
Then what should we do?
“从正面绕回来，让大家乐一乐”
"Bring him back from the front for a laugh!"
怎么办？继续当官叹！
We can continue to be civil servants!
遇事要多动脑筋
Use your brain, not brawn.
先动脑子后动手，明白吗？
Think twice before you make a move.
明白
Got it.
师爷
Counselor!
我们现在是做官的人了
We're government officials now.
不得再有匪气
We can't act like bandits!
师爷，当县长最要紧的是什么？
What is a good governor's virtue?
忍耐！
Forbearance.
"Goose Town"
当了县长
and play-act governor.
我还得拉拢豪绅
I still have to play boot-licker to the rich,
还得巧立名目
make up silly excuses,
还得看他的脸色
and do things at his whim.
我不成跪着要饭的了吗？
Doesn't that make me a beggar?
就成现在这样了
it's taken root and sprouted leaves.
我爹说了
Pop said to me,
有冤鼓，就说明有冤！
we need this to convene court.
他说他要判个案！
He wants to try a case.
哪儿有冤呐？
What case?
谁敢有冤呐？
Has someone filed a complaint?
这都一百多年了
It's been here for 100 years.
你要把它砍了，把鼓露出来
If you now unveil the drum,
不定出多大冤呐？
who knows what case it may bring?
别砍啦！你爹他人呢？
Where's your old man?
睡觉！
In bed.
跟谁睡啊？怎么还睡啊？
At this hour? Who with?
鼓呢？
What happened?
Where is it going?
叫你别砍吧，把鼓给砍跑了
Look what you've done!
鼓鼓鼓鼓！
Drum...!
躲开
Out of my way!
这鼓怎么跟着我呀
It's homing in on me!
救命呀…！大人
Help! Help!
可惜了老子的酒
My wine is ruined,
老子的雅兴全让你给毁了
my mood destroyed!
全毁了！
Everything's spoilt!
改日我再收拾你
I'll deal with you another day.
鼓都捶破了
The drum is shattered!
说明你们俩很冤呐
So there must be a case to try!
升堂！
Court!
冤从何来？
How have you been wronged?
没冤！
I'm not.
有冤的说冤，没冤的那就散！散会
If no one is wronged, case dismissed!
冤！
Sir!
不是我冤，是武举老爷冤！
I have wronged Master Wu.
小的不长眼
I was careless.
在躲鼓的时候碰洒了武举老爷的酒
I ran into him and knocked over his wine.
害的武举老爷没有了胃口
Completely ruining his day.
小的应该给武举老爷赔礼，赔礼
I need to kowtow and apologise. Sorry!
老子不冤
That was nothing.
敢说你不冤
How dare you say nothing?
跪下！
Kneel!
这可是黄四郎的团练教头
He coaches Huang's militia.
跪不得
Go easy on him.
那这个穆扎在哪儿？
Where's this Mozart?
我留洋的时候要去哪找他？
How can I find him?
他呀，离咱们很远
He is far away from us.
怎么做，知道了吗？
Know what you have to do?
知道了
Yes.
谁让你去做的，你也知道了吗？
Who ordered you to do this?
知道了
Who, sir?
是老爷叫你去的吗？
Did I tell you to do it?
是，是老爷让我去的
Yes, sir. You did.
跟我们一块回山里吧
you must come and join our gang.
你可以继续当我的母亲
Then you can continue to play mother.
人往高处走，水往低处流！
One should always aim high.
你说她怎么不害怕啊？
Why isn't she afraid?
有点傻吧
She must be daft.
为什么要枪毙麻匪？
Know why we shot these bandits?
因为他们抢官车，劫县长！
It's because they ambushed the Governor.
枪毙他们，就是为了让大家明白
Let this be a lesson to all!
准！大哥
Exactly!
我还在娘胎里的时候
A fortune teller told my mother
算命先生就指着我娘的肚子说
before I was even born!
是不是把县长给阉了？
I'll cut his balls off!
钻石！…
Diamonds!
我的两颗钻石！
My two diamonds!
老爷放心！你要的钻石
Don't worry, sir!
我这就给你弄回来
I'll retrieve your diamonds.
对不起
I'm sorry.
我应该的
My pleasure, sir.
明白不明白，为什么派你去？
Know why I'm sending you?
因为我死了
It's because I'm already dead.
为什么你会死呢？
Do you know why?
因为我把老爷给供出来了
I shouldn't have implicated you.
对楼！如果你活着，早晚都会死
Right! If you are alive, you'll eventually die.
如果你死了
But if you're dead,
这孩子将来最大缺点
He said my Achilles heel
就是不会装糊涂！
would be my inability to play act!
大哥，我还能改吗？
Can I change it?
改不了！天生的
No way! It's in your genes!
你看看这位师爷就是装糊涂的高手
But our counselor is a born actor!
把钱说成刀
Confusing dollar with dolls?
钱，是什么钱？
What is dollar?
是美元！
American money!
你看你看！装糊涂的天才啊！
A genius when it comes to play acting.
师爷，敬你的
Counselor, cheers!
谢黄老爷颂扬
Thanks for your compliment, sir.
容老弟真的糊涂一回
Allow me to play the fool for once.
剿匪成功之后，追回的烟土
After defeating the bandits,
我们只要两成就够！
we'll take just 20% of any opium recovered.
不行！对半开！
No, I insist 50-50!
为表诚意，预祝剿匪凯旋！
To show my sincerity,
一百八十万，马上送来！
I'll send over $1.8 million now.
无功不受禄，现在收钱太早
That's too soon. We haven't started yet!
黛玉，晴雯！
Marie, Claire!
大哥，美女我也不能要
Master, I can't take women.
美女不要，钱你也不要
No interest in money or women,
你要什么啊？
what do you want?
腿！
A runner.
什么腿啊？
What runner?
你不会装糊涂
You don't know how to play act.
明白，明白
I see, I see...
我也明白
Yes, me too.
该死的东西！
Stupid bitch!
花有重开日
While flowers can blossom again,
人无再少年
time lost will never return.
姑娘如花似玉
This girl is as delicate as jade.
大哥，怒不得啊！
Please don't be mad at her.
黄老爷，轻松点！
Master Huang, easy easy...
相见恨晚！
Shame we didn't meet until now!
姑娘、钻石一并送上！
Diamonds, the girl - they're all yours.
对抗官府之下场！
Never mess with the Governor!
县长来了，鹅城太平了！
Hail the Governor!
县长来了，青天就有啦！
Peace and justice is here!
师爷，说得好啊
Great speech!
你记得我跟你说过
Remember what I told you?
有时候死人比活人有用吧
The dead can be really handy.
是，死人是比活人有用
You're absolutely right.
霸气外露！
Such arrogance!
找死！
He's trouble.
刚进城就开枪
A show of force!
这不是二八开能打发走的
This one is a tricky customer!
先发制人？
Should we strike first?
不急
No hurry.
跟他耍耍
Let's toy with him.
不急，跟他耍耍
No hurry, let's toy with him!
算了吧！
Cut it out!
算了！
算了吧！
Cut it out! Cut it out!
算了算了！
算了吧！
Cut it out...
算了！!
Cut it out!
算你妈的吧！
Cut the bloody hell out!
胡千
Butler!
是，老爷！
Yes sir!
多拔他几颗牙
Take him to the dentist.
跟我一样，全镶成金的
Fix him up with gold teeth like mine.
是
Yes sir!
夫人
Madam!
兄弟我此番
The reason I am here,
只为劫财
is to get rich,
不为劫色
not to get laid.
同床
We share a bed,
但不入身！
but not our dreams.
有枪在此
Here's a pistol.
若是兄弟我…
Just in case,
有冒犯夫人的举动
I overstep my mark,
你可以随时干掉我
shoot me between the eyes.
起来！不准跪！
Stand up everyone!
皇上都没了，没人值得你们跪！
No one is worth kneeling to.
我也不值你们跪！
Least of all to me!
我来鹅城只办三件事
I've brought three things to Goose Town.
公平！
Justice,
justice,
还是公平！
and goddamned justice.
青天大老爷！
Hail, Governor!
站起来！不准跪！
Stand up! No kneeling!
这就对了
That's better.
不准跪？
No kneeling?
这哪是打我的屁股
He was not only flogging me,
这明明是打您的脸
he was slapping you in the face!
老爷，等我把屁股养好了
When my butts stop hurting,
我亲手给你报仇！
I will personally avenge you.
那就把卖凉粉的叫来
Summon the noodle vendor.
县长喜欢判案
If our governor loves to try,
就安排一点案子给他判叹
we'll give him a case to try.
唉！我带夫人来的
I've brought my wife with me.
再收姑娘不方便
So I can't take her home.
那钻石送夫人
Then take the diamonds for your wife.
好！我先替她收着
I accept them on her behalf.
起来吧
Get up.
不是黛玉和晴雯吗？
I thought you'd summoned two girls.
怎么就来了一名女子？
How come there's only her?
莫非她就叫黛玉晴雯？
You mean she is Marie-Claire?
说你不会装糊涂吧
You are really naive!
起了个东洋名字
She's adopted a fashionable name.
黛玉晴雯子！
It's Marie-Claire!
全死了！
There goes the last of them!
为什么朝我床上开枪？
Why did you target my bed?
黄老爷说你霸气外露
Master said you're arrogant,
危险！
a threat!
回去给他带个话，告诉他
Take him a message:
他喜欢让人假死这一套
While he likes people to fake death,
正好，我也喜欢让人多死几回这一套
I'm fond of killing people more than once!
贱货，骚货，妹子，贱货！
Whore! Bitch! Vixen! Tramp!
就是时间不够
If I'd more time,
要不然我活活把你给搞死了！
I'll put you in your place!
好啊，来呀
Come on!
看你怎么办
I dare you!
你就只剩下一张嘴！
You're all talk!
写几个烂戏本的老色鬼！
A perverted, dirty old man.
不是我出钱
Could you have bought the post
谁给你买官当县长啊？
without my money?
你别逼急我了
Don't piss me off!
我还真觉得那个土匪挺有本事的
I think the bandit is more able!
他算什么本事啊？
What do you mean?
比你有本事
He's got more balls than you!
早烂醉如泥了
He's good at getting drunk!
这才是真本事
These will make your day!
杀了你，我还怎么睡啊
I don't sleep with dead bodies!
我不能酒后欺负一个寡妇
I won't take drunken advantage of a widow,
是跟你睡
so I'll just sleep next to you,
不是睡你
not with you!
我居然上了你们的当！
Holy smoke! I was fooled!
你和武举人都是假死是吧？
You and Wu both faked death!
不错
That's right.
为什么冒充麻匪？
Why dressed up as a bandit?
老子就是麻匪，张麻子是我大哥
I'm a bandit. "Pocky" Zhang's my boss!
那你是老几呀？
What's your rank, then?
老三
I am Three!
老三，你出名了
Three, you've hit big time!
有人冒充你了！
You've got yourself a fake!
别听他废话了，大哥
Chief, don't listen to his bullshit!
六子就死在他手上
He plotted Six's death.
你让我一枪崩了他
Let me shoot him now!
大哥？
Chief?
是你大哥张麻子派你来的
Were you sent by "Pocky" Zhang?
还是你老爷黄四郎派你来的？
Or by Master Huang?
不能说错啊！
I want the right answer!
黄老爷 为什么？
- Master Huang. - Why?
他让我们假扮麻匪在城里抢劫
We commit crimes posing as bandits,
他逼县长下令剿匪
forcing governors to launch expeditions.
师爷，高！
A wise counselor!
县长，硬！
A tough governor!
黄老爷又高又硬！
Master, you're both wise and tough.
你到底是不是张麻子？
Are you really "Pocky" Zhang?
要说你是吧
Supposing that you are.
扭断刘都统大腿
You've already made a fortune
赚那么多钱
from "crippling" Liu's runners.
何苦进城当县长呢？
Why bother with Goose Town?
要说你不是吧…
But if you are someone else...
恩人？
Saviour?
今晚，杀鸡取卵！
Kill the chicken and take the eggs.
一定要在县长的床上
Let him die in his own bed.
不要让人以为吃了我的饭
Don't kill him on his way home
死在我家里，死在半路上
after dining as my guest.
明白！
Understood!
哪个是鸡？
Who is the "chicken"?
县长！
The Governor.
那么卵呢？
And the "eggs"?
给你报仇
and avenge your death.
可是中途我改了主意
But I've changed my mind.
鱼死网破报不了仇
I can't take revenge this way.
弟兄们不能再死人了
I can't risk more lives.
大哥，你怎么在这儿啊？
Chief, we're looking for you.
你怎么让我们撤了呀？
Why did you signal retreat?
黄四郎听见你们吹的哨声
Huang heard your whistling.
我就绝对安全了
I knew that I was safe.
去吧，我跟六子单独待会儿
Leave, I want to spend time alone with Six.
今天我算明白了
It has finally dawned on me,
为什么当初我会上山当麻匪
why I became a bandit in the first place.
就是因为跟这帮东西玩不起
I was no match for these people.
现在为了你，我必须玩得起
But I must take them on at their own game now,
还得玩得赢
and to win for you.
谁？
What the heck?
偷我的钻石！
You stole my diamonds.
这石头是给你的吗？
They're not meant for you.
是给县长夫人的
They're a gift for Mrs. Governor!
咱们俩谁是县长？
Which of us is the Governor?
谁是县长？
Who's the Governor?
我问你呢，谁是县长？
Tell me who's the Governor!
你是要杀我？
You want to kill me?
还是要睡我？
Or to sleep with me?
有什么不一样吗？
Is there a difference?
不一样啊！
It's different!
那就先睡，再杀
I can bed you first, and kill you later.
那还是杀了我吧
Then you'd better kill me now.
您要放我回去？
Letting me off again?
只有你的话他听得懂
He can only understand words you say.
大哥，可您到底是？
Chief, you're...
不错，张麻子！
Yes, "Pocky" Zhang.
江湖豪情，侠胆柔肠之大腿
Master Huang's a runner of exceptional courage!
哥！ 弟！
- Brother! - Brother!
你的腿，就是我的腿
We can run side by side!
你的腿，就是我的命
We'll run for our lives!
有道是，江湖本无路
Roads won't exist in this world of chaos,
有了腿，便有了路！
unless people like us run on them!
你永远都活着
you may live on forever!
明白
Understood.
杀鸡取卵！
Kill the chicken, take the eggs!
师爷，大哥呢？
Where's Chief?
马上，喝醉了
Punch drunk!
人呢？哪儿呢？
Where is he?
刚才还说话呢！
We're still chatting just now!
我也喝醉了
I must be drunk, too!
回来跟你算帐
I'll sort you out later.
没在马上么？是不是掉路上了？
He must've fallen off the horse.
听说你睡觉了
I heard that you slept.
你抬起头来跟我说话
Look up when you speak.
听说你昨天睡觉了
I heard that you slept last night.
我哪天不睡觉啊！
I sleep every goddamned night!
你看着我说话
Look at me when you speak.
听说你跟土匪睡觉了
You slept with the bandit?
睡了！你不想知道我们怎么睡的吗？
Do you want a blow-by-blow account?
对，怎么睡的？
Tell me more.
一个青楼女子，跟一个土匪头子
When a seasoned pro meets a bandit chief,
什么睡法都能有
anything could happen!
嘘什么嘘？
What now?
你这个不要脸的骚窑姐，妹子，贱货
Whore! Bitch! Vixen! Tramp!
你说什么！
What did you call me?
千爷，别打了
Butler, hold your fire!
赶紧回去备银子吧！
We need time to prepare the ransom.
她是我老婆！
She was my wife.
我是县长！ 让他进来
- I am the governor! - Let him in.
我就是马邦德！
I am Ma Bangde!
县长如何了？县长如何了？
Is the Governor okay?
你们追！一个麻匪也不能跑！
Give chase! Don't let anyone get away.
天杀的麻匪
Those goddamned bandits!
伤天害理
Scum of the earth!
县长刚刚上任，竟和他的夫人双双…
The Governor has only just arrived...
我说我当不了这个县长！
Said I didn't want to be a governor,
你非得给我花钱买这个官！
but you still bought me this post!
现在官倒是到手了
The governership is now mine,
你倒这么走了！
but you've left me on my own.
她是我老婆！
She was my wife.
我就是县长
I am the governor!
我就是马邦德！
I am Ma Bangde!
你呀，太年轻了
You're too hot-headed.
爹，今天你这县长干得真漂亮
Pop, you were brilliant today.
打武举人打得真过瘾
Flogging that martial scholar was a hoot!
将来我也想当县长
I'd love to be a governor one day.
你不能当县长，也不许当土匪
I don't want you to be a bandit or politician.
你爹死的时候把你交给我
When your father entrusted you to me,
我答应过他，要让你有出息
I promised I'd raise you properly.
那我当什么才有出息？
Then what should I do?
当学生！读书，多听这个
Study and learn to enjoy this.
没声啊！
There is no sound!
我不能…
Then I must not...
让她再守活寡
Ieave her alone uncomforted.
这是第一步
That's my first move.
三步之内…
Within three...
要不让他们滚蛋走人
they'll either leave with tails between their legs,
要不让他们跪下当狗！
or stay and become our poodles!
对，非常对
Right, absolutely right.
老爷，您找我？
You're looking for me, sir?
官府的人还没来？
Have you entertained our new officials yet?
没有
Not yet.
县长不缥妓？
The Governor doesn't frequent brothels?
不好色的县长，不一定是好县长
He'll never make a good governor.
我就是不好色！
I don't indulge much in sex.
所以您当不了县长
So you won't make a good governor either.
我当不了县长？
Why is that so?
县长哪能跟您比呀
The two bear no comparison!
他只是流水的县长
Governors come and go.
您才是铁打的老爷
But you, sir, will always be our godfather!
你真会讲话
You speak well!
他们一定会来，你要好好记住
I'm sure they will come.
他们讲的每一句有用的话
Eavesdrop their every conversation,
都要回来跟我汇报
report their every move.
是
Yes.
走吧，你不要变成小凤仙哦
Go now. Just don't become a Mata Hari!
老爷，谁是小凤仙？
Who's Mata Hari, Master?
小凤仙都不知道还当妓女
What kind of whore are you?
那可是名震京城，誉满全国的妓女
She's the world's most infamous double agent!
你们出去吧
You two can leave.
县长此刻正怀抱夫人，共枕同眠
Now the Governor is in bed with his wife.
让他睡最后一个安稳觉
Let him enjoy one more night in peace!
县长公子，以身试法
The Governor's boy is in trouble,
讲茶大堂，恭迎大驾！
your presence is requested at the teahouse.
讲茶大堂？县衙不是判案的地方吗？
Why don't they convene at the magistracy?
你这个县衙是摆设
The magistracy is just for show.
判案只有去讲茶大堂！那才是真县衙！
All cases are tried at the teahouse.
六爷
Master Six,
你吃了两碗的粉
you've eaten two bowls of jelly,
不刮穷鬼的钱你收谁的呀？
Who are your victims, then?
谁有钱赚谁的
The rich, of course.
当过县长吗？
Ever been a Governor?
没有
No.
我告诉你！
Listen carefully!
县长上任，得巧立名目
You have to devise ways to raise money,
拉拢豪绅，缴税捐款
Make the rich pay first,
他们交了，才能让百姓跟着交钱
townsfolk will follow suit.
得钱之后，豪绅的钱如数奉还
Then reimburse the rich with what they paid,
百姓的钱，三七分成！
and split the rest 30-70!
怎么才七成啊？
We only get 70?
七成是人家的！
No, the rich get 70.
能得三成还得看黄四郎的脸色
We get 30 at Huang's discretion.
谁的脸色？
At whose discretion?
他！
Him.
他？!
Him?
我大老远的来一趟
I come all this way,
就是为了看他的脸色？
only to become his running dog?
对！
Correct.
我好不容易劫了趟火车
It's hard enough robbing your train,
老子是光绪三十一年
During the reign of the last Emperor,
皇上钦点的武举人
I was bestowed a Martial Scholar.
论官职，比你官大
My rank was higher than yours.
你应该给老子跪下
You should kneel in front of me!
跪下！
Kneel!
跪不跪？
还皇上！
This is bullshit!
哪个皇上？我见过吗？
The last Emperor? Have I ever met him?
你要是个文举人
If you'd been a Literary Scholar,
他应该给你磕两百个头
he'd have to kowtow 200 times.
可惜你只是个武举人
But as a Martial Scholar,
他只能给你磕一百个头
you'll get only 100 kowtows.
现在他两百个头磕完了
Since he has already done 200,
你还他一百个
you've to return 100 kowtows.
可我只磕了两个
But I've only kowtowed twice!
两个也得还你一百个
Does it really matter?
才能让我看得见
so that we can all see.
六爷，让大家看看是一碗还是两碗
Show us if there is one or two bowls.
拉！
Out with it!
六爷，碗！
Here's a bowl, sir.
看见了吧！看见了吧！
See! Can you see?
是不是只有一碗！
One bowl!
There's only one bowl, right?
你早说不就得了吗
Let's be frank.
他要个公平
He wants to be treated fairly.
你不是欺负老实人吗？
It's wrong to bully a commoner.
告诉我，你是老实人吗？
Are you an honest person?
我是
Yes, I am...
那你就说实话，我到底吃了几碗粉？
How many bowls did I eat?
你告诉他！
Tell him!
你说不说？
Speak up!
拿枪吓唬一可怜的，卖凉粉的
Stop threatening this poor man with a gun!
有枪是吧？谁没有枪啊！
Who doesn't carry a gun around here?
孙守义
Noodle vendor!
大声说，他吃了几碗
How many bowls did he eat?
守义，在座所有的乡亲
Everyone in this teahouse,
都会为你和你的家人作主的
will bear witness on your behalf.
大声说，几碗
Speak up! How many?
两碗
Two bowls.
你是一个恶人！
You're nasty!
比恶是吧，我比你还恶
But I dare you to match me!
都看好了啊
Take a good look!
今我肚子里要有两碗粉
If there are two bowls of jelly in me,
我白死
I'll die!
杀了他，六子白死
Don't let Six die in vain!
我没有杀他，他自己捅自己的！
I didn't do it. He stabbed himself.
我们在打赌
We'd a wager.
他输了
He lost.
大哥，你让我一枪崩了他！
Let me blast his head off!
你不敢杀我！你不能杀我！
You wouldn't dare! You can't do it.
黄四郎就想看你这样！
Huang is provoking you.
一脸的败相！
He wants you to lose your head.
杀了他就是输，不杀还能赢
We'll lose if we kill him now.
放人
Let him go.
杀人诛心，杀人诛心！
You must destroy Huang's soul!
师爷说得对 放人
- Pop, he's right. - Let him go!
刀进了肚子，那凉粉还是凉粉？
He stabbed himself? What about the jelly?
是
Yes
不是
and no...
我就想知道，凉粉到底还是不是凉粉
Tell me if it was still jelly.
是凉粉！
Yes, it was.
过来过来
Come over here.
那么…
And...
人死了？
is he dead?
死了
Yes.
所以…你就把我供出来了？
Did you implicate me?
我是用老爷的名字吓唬他们
I did invoke your name.
他们被吓着了么？
Were they scared?
他们说杀人诛心！
They said to kill, a person's soul must first be destroyed.
杀人还要诛心？
Murder? Soul destruction?
好可怕啊！
How awful.
六弟，四哥发誓替你报仇！
Brother, I vow to avenge you!
六弟，五哥发誓替你报仇！
Brother, I swear I'll avenge you!
六哥，七弟发誓替你报仇！
Brother, I vow to avenge you!
二哥喝醉了，他让我带话
Two is drunk. I am pledging for him.
二哥发誓替你报仇！
He will avenge your death, too.
六弟，三哥发誓替你报仇！
Brother, I swear to avenge you!
二哥没喝醉，他生气了！
Two is sober, he's just pissed off!
大哥不想让大伙拼命
Chief doesn't want to risk our lives.
命都不拼，还算麻匪吗？
Are we boy scouts or what?
你磕头！你数数！
You kowtow, and you do the counting.
一二三四五六…
One, two, three, four...
青天大老爷！
Hail, Governor!
这帮买官的县长，就知道捞钱
Politicians only know how to bully.
不该一进城就枪毙麻匪
You shouldn't have shot those bandits.
他们一定会报复你的
They'll take revenge for sure.
不哭，不哭
Don't cry.
她是为鹅城死的
She died for Goose Town.
得厚葬她呀
She deserves a proper burial!
得让所有的乡绅都过来
Invite every townsfolk to attend.
有粗有细啊！
I am impressed!
三天之内，钱不到就撕票！
We'll kill the hostages in 3 days!
记着，我是九筒！
Remember, I am Nine!
这活办的真爽快！
That was quite a show.
像真的吗？ 像！
- Almost pass for real! - Sure.
要是有人再流点血就更像真的了！
It'll be more convincing with some blood.
对！
Right!
有这个必要吗？
Was that necessary?
有这个必要吗？有这个必要吗？
Was that really necessary?
给我打！给我狠狠打！
Shoot! Give them hell!
六子，黄四郎今天死了三条狗
Three of Huang's dogs died today.
我知道，狗命抵不了你的命
I know they're not worthy of you.
我本来带着弟兄们
I was going to lead our brothers,
要跟黄四郎拼个鱼死网破
engage Huang in a deadly duel,
"Master Six rests here in peace"
…放下今生的担子
...to be relieved of life's burden.
我们就亲切的将他放入土中
Thus we commit their bodies to earth.
他们本是尘土
From which they came,
现在，他们依然是尘土
and do now return.
我们知道，这一切的生命气息
We know we can place ourselves,
都在永生的慈爱的天父手里
in the hands of our Father in Heaven,
而且他应允将永生…
who has promised us eternal life.
我们是张麻子张大爷的队伍！
We're from "Pocky" Zhang's gang.
要钱！不要命！
We're here for the money.
各位乡绅受惊了
Sorry for the intrusion!
我们今天就是来找几个人
We're looking for...
黄四郎！城南两大家族！站出来
Huang, heads of families, show yourselves!
胡万？
Hu Wan?
神父，打扰了
Father, our apologies.
各位父老
Ladies and gentlemen,
剩下的事情就与你们无关了
the rest has nothing to do with this.
再见
Leave!
入袋
Gag them!
起来
Get up!
好汉！我是本县县长
I'm the governor of this county.
要绑，绑我吧
I volunteer to be your hostage.
你不说话不行吗！
Just shut up!
留着你的命，活着替我们收钱
We spare you to deliver our ransom.
三天之内，钱到，放人
Three days, pay up and they go home.
钱不到，撕票 打死我吧
- If not, they die. - Shoot me first!
别打别打！ 打死我！
- Stop it! - Shoot me first!
找打是吧
You're asking for it.
打…！
Beat him up!
你怎么这么多嘴啊！
You talk too much!
让你多嘴
I'll teach you a lesson!
你装模做样的带我的九筒干什么
Stop messing with my mask!
别把事给我办砸了！
Don't screw things up.
带走！
Take them away!
三天收不到钱，麻匪可是要撕票的！
Otherwise they will kill the hostages.
撕！让他们撕！
Let them kill the hostages.
一定要让他们撕
In fact, I want them dead!
替身就是为我干这个的
Why do you think I need a double?
这个钱，我一分钱都不出！
I'll not pay any ransom.
不过两大家族的钱
But the families will pay up.
一定会过你们的手
You'll get your money for sure.
弟弟
Brother,
不要为我担心啊！
I'm fine.
千万不要为我担心！
Don't worry about me.
老爷，我怀疑胡万投靠了张麻子
Hu Wan must have defected to Zhang.
一定要找到胡万！
He must be found,
活要见人，死要见尸
dead or alive!
骗豪绅，刮百姓
Creating more chances for Huang to swindle.
然后呢？
And then?
没了 没了？
- That's all. - Really?
其他事我真不知道！
I don't know anything else!
可大哥您脸上没麻子
Where are your pockmarks?
黄四郎脸上有四吗？
Does your boss have "Huang" inscribed on his face?
懂了
That's true.
兄弟
My friend,
我是张麻子这件事
you must not tell anyone,
要替我永远保密
that I am "Pocky" Zhang.
永远保密！
You have my word!
我说我当不了县长
I never want to be a governor,
你非花钱让我买这个官
but you still bought me this post!
现在官被人家抢走了
The position has been usurped,
你也就这么死了！
and now you're dead too.
黄四郎带人来了
Huang has brought his militia.
说是要帮我们打麻匪
Wanting to fight bandits with us.
砸了
Yes, game's up.
我怎么觉得…刚开始啊！
The fun has only just begun.
阿门！
Amen!
放人！
Release them.
给你们留个纪念，不准回头，滚！
Here's a souvenir. Don't look back. Scram!
夫人，你要是晚走两天
Ma'am, if you're still alive,
就能亲眼看见了
you'd see this for yourself.
嫂子要是不走，这钱都到不了这桌上
If she was alive, there'll be nothing here.
对，我老婆的命换来的这些钱
She traded her life for this.
那我们家小六子的命不算命啊？
Doesn't Six's life count?
那不一样！
It's different.
怎么就不一样啊？
Goddamned it isn't!
夫人！
My wife.
谁夫人啊？
Whose wife?
我夫人！
Mine.
你夫人怎么了？
What about her?
夫人是被黄四郎杀死的
She was murdered by Huang.
你们家六爷自残，自杀！
But Six died at his own hands.
我一枪崩了你
I'll shoot you dead,
你敢说我们家小六子，找死啊！
for demeaning our Six!
老二你把枪放下
Two, put down your gun.
别拿枪对着我
Stop pointing your gun at me!
我见过土匪，没见过练肌肉的土匪
I've never seen bandits as dumb as you!
笑什么啊，别笑，别笑！
Stop laughing! Cut it out.
我是说你们家六爷，你们家六爷这样
I didn't belittle Six! He had courage!
那是英雄
He was a hero!
是，是英雄
Yes, he was heroic.
我老婆睡着觉，就没醒过来
My wife went to sleep and died in bed.
师爷不哭，嫂子也是英雄
Don't cry! Your wife was heroic, too.
各位哥哥，咱们为什么来了？
Brothers, why are we here?
钱啊
To get rich!
老天爷都能当，还收拾不了一个黄四郎？
If I am God, ridding him should be a piece of cake.
是他！ 老三！
- It's him. - Three!
装箱
Pack them!
不见钱不放人啊！
No one goes until we get his ransom.
千哥，忍着！
Butler, stay calm!
一二三！
One, two, three...
黄四郎在里头
Huang is in there!
一二三！
One, two, three...
你抱着我夫人学我哭的时候
You plotted this scheme
就想到这招了
over my wife's dead body?
钱到了吗？
Have we succeeded?
到了
Yes, we have.
走啊！
So let's leave!
走啊
Let's go.
那你还哭什么呀？
Why are you still in tears?
我可以不哭
I'm overjoyed.
大哥，什么时候走？
Chief, when do we leave?
你不就是想当老天爷吗？
Haven't you always wanted to play God?
是啊
Yes.
这跟收拾黄四郎有什么关系呀？
What has it got to do with Huang?
还为了一个女人
and we're bickering over a broad!
我进城那天，带头敲鼓的是你吧
You're the lead drummer at my inauguration?
姑娘，贵姓？
What's your name?
不客气，花姐
Call me Flora.
不是姓黄吧？
Are you related to Huang?
不姓！是黄四郎把我买来的
No, he bought me.
城门口贴的那些告示
There are posters by the city gate.
知道是什么意思吧？
Know what they're for?
通缉张麻子的
Bounty offers for "Pocky" Zhang.
我就是张麻子
I am "Pocky" Zhang.
麻匪发的，铁证如山！
The bandits were behind this.
用面具的就是麻匪？我们也有面具
Is it because of the masks? We have masks too!
那就是县长？
Then it must be the Governor!
有钱不赚，发给穷人
He is giving money to the poor?
这像是个买官的县长做的事吗？
No bogus governor would do that.
今天，我要你们扮成麻匪
I want you to dress up as bandits.
跟他们一模一样
Exactly like them.
他们怎么发，你们就怎么抢！
What they give out, you take away.
搞乱他们！
Let's cause havoc!
明白！
Understood.
三步棋必治他于死地
I'll have him checkmate in 3 moves!
老爷，三步棋，咱们都已经走完了
But we've made 3 moves already.
是吗？
Really?
逼死小六子，杀鸡取卵…
Driving Six to death, killing the chicken for the eggs...
替身这么有用啊！得空帮我也找一个
A double is useful. Find me one, too.
张麻子，你真是死不要脸
Pocky, have you no shame?
玩砸了！
The game's up!
砸了吗？
Really?
这个，我认识
I think I know her.
都来都来，我会安排
Certainly. I'll take care of it.
"Here lies Madam Governor"
见过麻匪真面目的，必死无疑！
Whoever sees a bandit's face has to die.
这可是你下的令
It's your own rule.
师爷
Counselor.
第一个见过麻匪真面目的人
The first to see our faces
是你！
was you!
事还没办呢就起内证！
Our mission is only half accomplished,
现在我要走的新三步
I'm talking about 3 new moves!
第一步，到省城查清马邦德
First, check out the Governor.
我总觉得他不像是个买官的县长
He doesn't act like someone who'd buy a post.
起码，不姓马！
At least, he's not Ma Bangde.
胡万的事怎么样了？
Have you found Hu Wan?
胡万？还没找到
Hu Wan? Not yet.
你怎么可能说还没有找到
How come he is still missing?
老爷你放心，我会去找他，继续找
Don't worry, sir. I'll find him.
你晓不晓得…
Do you know...
我多么的想他
how much I miss him?
黄老爷盼咐我们把他们搞乱
On master's order, let's wreak havoc!
看老子怎么把他们搞乱
Let's show how we can mess things up!
收到银子了？
Did you get your share?
收到了
Yes.
那你打算怎么感谢我们
How are you going to thank us?
怎么感谢都…都行
Any way you like.
怎么感谢都行？你说的！好！
Any way I like? Great, you said it!
知道我们…为什么会给你发银子吗？
Know why we gave you money?
因为麻匪爷对我们好
It is because you're benevolent.
对你好？
Benevolent?
还没好透！
We can do even better!
透！透！透！
Batter! Batter!
青天大老爷做主啊！
Governor, we want justice!
砸了你们！砸了！
It's all over! We're finished!
兔子都知道不吃窝边草
Even rabbits wouldn't do this.
六个人，还当着人家丈夫
Six men, in front of her husband,
还让人看
and in broad daylight!
呸！恶心
Disgusting!
我都关着灯！
I've never even done this with lights on!
这种事你们可以花点钱嘛！
If you're desperate, paid for it!
花点！
Be extravagant!
哪怕缥呢！
Visit a brothel!
花不了多少钱！
It won't cost much!
哪怕偷偷摸摸的
You don't even have to be discreet.
简直就是土匪
This is stupid!
土匪都不如！
You're worse than bandits!
还说让人家百姓夸你们好
And we'd wanted to leave a good impression!
不走！
We're not.
钱不是黄四郎送来的
This is not Huang's money.
大哥，两大家族的钱不算钱啊？
But the money's still good!
我要的是黄四郎的钱！
I want Huang's fortune.
你不刮穷人的钱，也不要大户的钱…
You refuse to take money from rich or poor...
六子，夫人，两条命
The blood debt of Six and Madam,
必须黄四郎来偿！
must be repaid by Huang!
你这是玩命啊！赌徒！
You're gambling with our lives!
这就算赌了？
You call this a gamble?
算！就是！还赌不赢
Yes, and you'll end up a loser!
人不走
We're not leaving.
钱也都不要了！
We don't want this money either.
发出去！
Give them away.
可是，大哥
But Chief...
这钱你都发给谁呢？
Who do you want to give this to?
发给穷人叹！
To the poor.
那谁是穷人啊？
Who are the poor?
谁穷，谁就是穷人
Those in dire need.
劫我的时候，你戴的就是九筒
You wore "Nine" when you ambushed me.
我这是多少？
What am I wearing now?
你自己摸摸
Feel it for yourself.
洲卜产卜 一同
"One"!
过瘾吗？
Fun, isn't it?
过瘾！
Brilliant!
这就能骑？
I can ride that?
我们在上海骑过！
We rode one once in Shanghai.
你们俩去过上海？
You have been to Shanghai?
浦东
Pudong!
不信，骑上准倒！
I'm sure you'd fall over.
来！试试！
Come on. Try it.
大哥，你是了解我的
You know me,
如果是我…
If it was me,
不会有人活着来告状
she wouldn't have lived to squeal.
大哥你是了解我的
You know me.
我老五虽然岁数最大
I may be the eldest,
我…我至今…
but I am...
俗称处男
still a virgin.
别看着我呀
Stop staring at me!
大哥，你是了解我的
You know me well.
如果我出手…
If I was responsible,
那趴在桌子上的
the one on the receiving end,
应该是她老公
would have been her husband!
我听出来了，你们都个个身怀绝技
Each of you is so unique.
但是…
But...
有人骗了我
I've been betrayed.
谁呀？谁呀？
By who?
老汤
Tang!
这么明显的事，一个师爷看不出来？
How could he overlook the obvious?
这明明是黄四郎狗狼养的找人冒充的
Huang is behind this scam.
他今天很反常
Tang's not behaving properly.
心里一定有鬼
He must be up to something.
出来！起来！站起来！
Come out! Stand up!
你最近跟什么人吃过饭？
Who have you been seeing lately?
见过黄四郎？
Master Huang?
不许动！举起腿来！
Don't move! Raise your legs.
我也认识
So do I!
给她发点钱吧
Let's give her some money.
干什么呀？
Hang on!
大哥说了，发穷人！她不穷
She is not exactly poor, is she?
那你说，谁算穷人？
So who are the poor?
穷人？那就得被逼得卖儿卖女！
Those who're forced to sell their own children.
她，就是被穷人卖掉的女儿！
Correct! She was sold by her parents.
对呀！
Make sense!
原来县长的人是麻匪！
So you're bandits in disguise!
我们就想给你发点钱！
We've come to give you money.
杀！必须的！
Kill her. No option!
你是个孩子？
You're a child?
几岁？ 八岁！
- How old are you? - Eight!
出来！
Come out!
这是八岁？!
He's eight?
没人信！我都不信！
I find it hard to believe myself!
三岁跟他妈一样高
As tall as Mom when he was three.
五岁就跟我一样高，八岁就这样了
Taller than me when he was five...
你妈！你妈！
Screw you!
妈！妈！
Mom, mom!
你妈！
Screw you!
敢打俺娃！
Hands off my boy!
你妈！ 你妈！
- Screw you! - Screw you, too!
你妈！
Screw you!
这是你亲妈？
She's your mother?
是我妈
Yes, she is.
这是你亲爹？
And he's your dad?
我家的事关你屁事啊！你妈！
None of your goddamned business.
你妈！
Stop it!
嫂子！怎么回事？
Ma'am, what's going on?
我是来要钱的，不给钱我不走
I come for money. I won't leave until he pays.
不给钱不走
He owes you?
这个老骗子，八年前在俺山西开矿
It was eight years ago in Shanxi.
骗了钱我就不说了，还骗了我的身子
This crook made me pregnant.
还不讲信誉
He is a man of poor repute.
他欠一屁股帐
Ran up a mountain of debts,
拍屁股走了
then vanished without trace.
人家问俺追帐，把我六岁的娃给绑了
Creditors kidnapped my younger son.
当人质呢，不给钱就撕票了！
He'll die if I don't clear his debts.
那不是我的
He's not my child!
那就是你的
He is!
不是我的 就是你的！
- He isn't. - He is!
是你的，我算着日子呢！
He is! I counted the days!
上来
Hop on!
走，走了！
Let's go!
自行车！
Bicycle!
可是，人肉的自行车
made of flesh and bones...
我来错地方了？
Have I come to the wrong place?
我来的不是时候？
Or at the wrong time?
接客
Serve your customers.
他们俩都是
They're my customers.
那是老三步了
Those were old moves!
就是一句话！恶心！
One word comes to mind: revolting!
钱肯定是赚不着了！
Our scheme is now in ruin!
恶心！恶心！
Disgusting!
恶心呐！恶心！
Filthy, nauseating...
呸！太恶心！
Revolting!
大哥，你是了解我的
You know me.
我从来不做仗势欺人的事
When it comes to this sort of thing,
我喜欢被动
I prefer to be passive...
大哥你是了解我的
You know me,
以我的习’惯
I am a lone wolf,
万事不求人
always acting on my own.
他戴的是几筒？
Which mask does he wear?
那不是麻匪扔进来的吗？
Isn't that bandit money?
难道他们俩是麻匪？
I wonder if they are also bandits.
他们不是麻匪，他们是官府的人
No, they work for the Governor.
你敢拿麻匪的钱给他们付帐？
How dare you pay their tab with bandit money?
别废话！先把人放了，快点！
Cut the crap! Let her go!
英雄救美！
White knights to the rescue!
就算他们是英雄，我也不是美人
I'm no damsel in distress.
就算我是美人，他们也不是英雄
They're no knights in shining armour.
老爷，毕竟他们是客人
After all, they're customers.
今天晚上的钱，我替他们付了
I've already settled their bills.
您不是常教育我们吗
You taught me yourself,
客人永远是上帝
customers are always supreme!
您说对吗？
Isn't that right?
对！
Yes!
Correct!
这就不是英雄救美了
Instead of knights coming to your rescue,
是美救英雄
they are being saved by a damsel.
你呀，快成小凤仙儿了
You're turning into a Mata Hari.
你得罪他了！
You've just pissed him off.
黄四郎不用得罪
He doesn't need to be pissed off.
他想让谁死
If he wants you dead,
谁就得死！
you die!
我刚才干嘛不一枪打死他呢？
I should've put a bullet through his head.
我一枪打死他不就完了么！
That would be the end of it.
别傻了！
Don't be silly.
大哥说了，留着他是要弄他的钱
Chief wants to go after his fortune.
既然想弄钱，那…
If you're here for the money, then...
你们干嘛到处发钱啊？
why are you giving it away?
这颜色行么
Is this the right colour?
把伞拿了
Lower the umbrella.
红倒是够了，你…你过来
The red is fine. Come over here!
先是绿，再弄红
First apply green, then red.
明白
Okay, got it.
明白这意思吧？
Understand?
你把那锁好了啊
Don't forget to lock up.
带上铁锹 知道了
- Bring the shovels. - Got it.
六把铁锹 知道了
- Six shovels! - Got it.
大哥你看我…
Chief, how do I look?
头不用梳了，脸够红，你过来！
Hair is fine. Face is flushed. Come here...
谁？！ 孩子！孩子
- Who's there? - A boy, my child!
孩子？ 我的！
- Your child? - Yes, mine.
把你的小儿子绑架了
and kidnapped your younger son.
不给钱就撕票
Threatening death...
撕票，所以我要钱呢！
Yes, so I need the money.
给钱！
Pay her.
钱，石头！
Money! The stones...
嫂子，初次见面
Just a small gift,
不成敬意
to mark our acquaintance.
石头我不要，不给钱我不走
I don't want these. I want real money.
你个傻…
You stupid idiot...
这比钱值钱！这是宝石
These diamonds are worth a fortune!
啊！真的！
No kidding?
自行车
Bicycle!
听不见
I can't hear you.
听不见！
I can't hear you!
城里麻匪火拼
There was a shoot-out.
死了六个人！咱们的人安然无恙！
Six killed. We're unscathed.
师爷，来来，请
Counselor, come take a look.
或许…是你的恩人呐
Your saviour may be among them.
死人的脸是绿的，加上点别的色
Apply that to a dead man's face
然后再变成这种红
will turn it into pinkish red.
明白了 明白了吧
- Got it. - Good.
绿
Green.
你过来
Come here.
绿在底下
Green is the base colour.
加上那个再变成这个就对了！
Add that and you'll get this!
明白了 明白吗
- Oh, I see... - Got it?
是这样的铁锹吗？
You want shovels like these?
锯短，装包里
Shorten them and put them in the bag.
多短？
How short?
能装包里
Short enough for the bag.
快去啊，六把啊
Hurry up! Six shovels!
去哪啊这是？
Where are you going?
怎么还扮上了？
What's with the make-up?
不是要跑吧？
Are you leaving for good?
你去不去？我们去发钱
Come with us to give out money?
九筒！
"Nine".
好极了！今晚不抢钱，杀人！
Splendid. Tonight we shall only kill!
杀谁？
Our target?
戴九筒的县长！
The Governor, wearing "Nine"!
杀县长不用戴面具，您等着验尸吧
Masked or not, consider this done!
回来！全给我戴上！
All of you, put on your masks!
麻匪火拼
"Firefight with bandits,
县长暴死
intrepid Governor killed!"
听着多么川页耳！
That would be music to my ears!
唱机都撂坏了
This gramophone was broken,
修好了
Now it is fixed.
这单活干完了，爹赚了钱
Once we're done here,
我送你去留洋
I'll let you study abroad.
东洋三年
3 years in the east,
西洋三年
3 in the west,
南洋三年
and 3 more in the south.
北洋，北洋三年
How about 3 years in the north?
傻孩子，你生在北洋，不必留了
No, you're born in the north.
这是谁吹的？
Who is this by?
听着像穆扎
I think it's Wolfgang.
他们那边叫穆扎
Sometime known as Amadeus.
咱们这边叫莫札特
We call him M-o-z-a-r-t.
你还能听出来是谁吹的呢？!
You can tell by listening?
得分时候
It depends.
什么时候？
On what?
是我自己要去的
It's my own plot.
没有人让我去，是我自己
There are no co-conspirators.
恩人！恩人！
Saviour! My saviour!
恩人！
Saviour!
你是叫我呢？
You're addressing me?
我什么时候成你恩人了？
Since when have I become your saviour?
不杀之恩为大恩！
You spared my life,
为报不杀之恩，我也救你一命
and I'll save yours in return.
哦？你快说
Do tell.
寡妇，不能睡啊！
Never sleep with a widow.
必有大灾！
It's very bad luck!
她…
She?
真的是寡妇么？
Is she really a widow?
我看着不像
She doesn't act like one.
我亲眼看见他丈夫淹死的
But I witnessed her husband drowned!
她已经成了寡妇
If she really is a widow,
就是恶霸请土匪！
It's just a meeting between two thugs!
项羽请刘邦啊！
It's like MacBeth hosting Banquo.
刘邦后来干什么去了？
What'd become of Banquo the guest?
当皇帝了
His son became king.
项羽呢？
And MacBeth the host?
那，赴宴？
So we should go.
赴宴！正好借机把黄四郎也笼络过来
We can also sound out Huang,
咱们三个联手一起捞钱
and see if we can work together.
“把家伙拿来”
"Bring the guns."
“换上黄家衣服跟我走”
"Dress up as Huang's militia and follow me."
明白
Got it!
“干掉黄四郎，给六子报仇”
"Kill Huang and avenge Six!"
明白
Understood!
老汤，你是把六子的死当捞钱的成本了？
You see Six's death as a shortcut to bonanza?
我看你当成本，赚的钱会更多
Perhaps your severed head can make us more.
这是什么意思？
What do you mean?
走！去会会你的新朋友
Let's go and meet your new pal.
立正！
Attention!
县长，师爷，大驾光临！有失远迎！
Governor, counselor! Welcome!
黄老爷的宅邸，竹林掩映，碉楼耸立
Master's citadel dominates Goose Town.
看清楚了，他们领头的戴几筒？
Which mask is their leader wearing?
九筒！
"Nine".
全都换上四筒！
Let's all change to "four"!
四筒是自己人，其他人全打死
Kill anyone who is not a "four"!
那边领头的戴的是几筒，看见了吗？
Which mask is their leader wearing?
四筒
"Four".
那咱们应该戴几筒，你知道吗？
Know what we'll be wearing, then?
明白
Got it.
他骗了人家钱
He swindled someone.
人家到你那去要帐
His victims tracked you down,
我们可是先来的
We're here first.
付钱了吗？
Have they paid?
自行车能算钱吗？
The "bicycle ride" doesn't count.
送客！
Show them out.
上次我给过你很多钱
But I've paid my dues.
什么钱？
With what?
窗户外边扔进来的银子？
Money you received through the window?
要慢，沉住气
you have to stay calm,
越慢越好
make it nice and slow.
你亲眼看见的？
You saw it with your own eyes?
我亲眼看见的！
Indeed.
你亲眼看见县长亲自带队出发？
You saw the Governor leading his men out?
我亲眼看见了！
Yes, with my own eyes.
你亲眼看见县长亲自带队出发去发钱？
They've gone to give out money?
黄老爷，你怎么在这啊？
Master Huang, what brings you here?
县衙我不能来吗？
Can I not visit the magistracy?
点上
Light it!
你们玩空城计，我就趁虚而入！
When the cat prowls, the mouse seizes control!
坐
Sit down!
县长呢？
Where's the Governor?
都是四筒，下不了手啊！
Everyone is a "Four"? I'm confused!
下不了手
I'm confused, too!
打雷天站在雨里头有点不讲究
It's bad to stay out in a thunderstorm.
太不讲究！
Yes, it's awful.
那改天再约，撤吧
Let's reschedule. Split!
撤！
Be in touch!
怎么撤？
What now?
从哪儿来，回哪儿去叹
It's back to square one.
好，从哪儿来，回哪儿去
Yes, square one.
一二三，撤！
Split! 1, 2, 3.
听，枪一响，就有人死
Listen! Someone's been shot.
有人死，就有人哭
Soon someone will mourn.
人一哭，就要说心里话
Mourning will lead to confessions.
说吧
Confess!
糟践东西，不去！
No, what a waste!
不去是吧 不去
- So you're not coming? - No.
那我告诉你
Now listen.
我这次去，可能回得来
This time, I may come back,
也可能回不来
but, then again, I may not.
我要是回来，你就跟我跑
If I do, you can leave with us.
我要是回不来，你就自己跑
If not, you plan your own getaway.
我亲眼看见了！
Yes, indeed.
我把人就埋在了那！
The bodies were buried there all along.
人埋在哪儿，事儿就出在哪儿！
I ensure the standoff was at their burial site.
事儿出在哪儿，黄四郎就得跟到哪儿！
That's where I led Huang to.
那你真是张麻子
I'm convinced you're "Pocky" Zhang.
坐！
Sit down.
我姓张
My name is Zhang.
知道
I know that.
叫牧之
Zhang Muzhi.
先弄死九筒！走！
Let's get rid of "Nine"!
你们看到了没有！这是当麻匪的下场！
Take a good look at a bandit's fate!
就算是我亲爹也得死！
I'd still have him shot
死有余辜！
if he was my father...
早晚！
sooner or later!
麻匪胡万又让黄老爷枪毙了五回
You just shot Hu Wan 5 more times.
大义灭亲？
You want to show justice?
杀人灭口？
Or to make sure he's dead?
杀人灭口，你就是麻匪的头子张麻子
Only "Pocky" Zhang would want to silence him.
要是大义灭亲，那好办！
If you'd only wanted to show justice,
接上他的腿
to fund an expedition to fix his broken leg!
大哥这个是惊喜啊
What a nice surprise!
小弟我愿意等你三天
I'm willing to wait 3 days.
黄老爷
Master Huang.
汤师爷是我的至爱
I adore my Counselor,
你可不能夺我所爱啊
I can't let you have him.
了然，了然
Fair enough.
六子
Six.
事已经办了九成了
We're almost there.
算七成吧
Say, 70% done.
今天我就派你二哥出城
I've asked Two to take off first.
到青石岭去接应我们
He'll wait for us at Emerald Creek.
乘l下的事，我会说到做到
I will keep my promise.
你明白了吧？
Know what you have to do?
明白
Yes.
一百八十万两银子到手
When $1.8 million is in hand,
我觉着小六子的仇算是报了
I'll consider Six avenged.
我觉着啊！
I feel that...
不光六子，夫人的仇也算报了
my wife's death is also avenged.
你不会真跟黄四郎玩命吧，恩人呐
Saviour, you still want to kill Huang?
我不是你恩人，黄四郎才是你恩人
I'm not your saviour. Huang is.
你是恩人，他不是！
You're my saviour. Not him.
你当时真的以为我死了？
Did you think I was lying dead back there?
没有！绝对没有
No, of course not.
没有？
Sure?
从没这么想过！
Never crossed my mind.
我可真算服了你了
I've to hand this to you.
去…去哪啊？不是发钱吗？
Aren't you just giving out money?
是发钱
Yes, we are.
还有…
By the way,
半夜的时候
at midnight tonight,
可能有人来找你
someone may come calling.
他要找你聊什么
Engage him in conversation.
你就跟他聊什么
Whatever the topics,
他怎么聊，你就怎么聊
just chat along with him.
但是…
But...
你至少有三句要说
You've at least three confessions to make.
我不该拿你的钻石送人
I shouldn't have given your diamonds away.
不是这句
Try again.
杀人诛心是我说的
I suggested "to kill someone, first destroy his soul".
也不是这句
Not that either.
鸿门宴要是我们请就好了
We should have hosted the banquet instead.
鸿门宴？
The banquet?
现在又成了你的恩人
Now he's your boss, too.
你给翻译翻译
Please act as our interpreter.
什么叫惊喜？
What is a "nice surprise"?
翻译翻译，什么叫惊喜？
Interpret for me.
这还用翻译？都说了…
There's nothing to interpret
我让你翻译给我听，什么叫惊喜
What on earth is a "nice surprise"?
不用翻译，就是惊京喜啊
It is what it is.
难道你听不懂什么叫惊喜
You just don't get it, do you?
我就想让你翻译翻译，什么叫惊喜！
Go ahead and interpret. What is it?
1京喜嘛…
A nice surprise!
翻译出来给我听
Translate for me!
什么他妈的叫惊喜！
What is this "nice surprise"?
什么他妈的叫他妈的惊喜！
What is this goddamned "nice surprise"?
什么他妈的叫惊喜啊？
What is this "nice surprise"?
惊喜就是三天之后
It means that in 3 days,
我出一百八十万，给你们出城剿匪
I'll put up $1.8 million for your campaign,
接上我的腿！
to fix my crippled leg!
明白了吗？
Is that clear?
这就是惊喜呀
That's the "nice surprise"!
翻译翻译
Interpret.
翻译翻译！
惊喜就是三天之后
The nice surprise is that,
给你一百八十万两银子，出城剿匪
he will give you $1.8 million in 3 days,
您才是我的恩人
No, you are my saviour.
既然我是你的恩人
If that is the case,
那就听恩人的话，揭开看看
remove his mask,
去吧，看看！
and have a good look.
来！照上照上！
Come on, lights!
什么情况？
What's going on?
什么情况？什么情况？
What's happening here?
胡万！
It's Hu Wan!
胡…胡万？
Hu Wan?
怎么会是胡万？
How come it's Hu Wan?
怪了
This is weird!
四筒啊
All those wearing "four"
全是黄家的人！
are my men!
麻匪呢？
Where are the bandits?
胡万，就是麻匪！
Where are they?
Hu Wan was a bandit!
麻匪，就是胡万！
He was one of them!
杀县长夫人，绑架豪绅
Murderers and kidnappers,
祸害鹅城百姓
those who terrorised Goose Town,
就是你黄老爷家的胡万！
were led by your own Hu Wan!
我说你为什么不出钱剿匪？
I wondered why you didn't fund the expedition.
原来你是贼喊捉贼啊！
You may even be the bandit chief himself!
你拿枪指着我？
You dare to turn your guns on me?
你拿枪指着我？!
你想跟我火拼？
Do you want a shoot-out?
因为你是好人
Because you're a good person.
我回来了
I came back alone.
碰上军阀混战，天下大乱
The country was in total chaos.
我只得浪迹江湖，落草为寇
So I became a bandit.
牧之也被叫成了麻子
They nicknamed me "Pocky".
可惜啊！多好的一个牧字
Shame! You're so handsome.
人们不愿意相信
People have an odd way of thinking,
一个土匪的名字叫牧之
that bandits shouldn't have proper names.
人们更愿意相信他叫麻子
They love calling their bandits "Pocky".
人们特别愿意相信
Not only that,
他的脸上应该长着麻子
they want their bandits scarred and scary.
这人可真够驴蛋的
People can be so ignorant.
我的故事…却是这样…
My own story started like this...
那年我也十七岁
I too was a tenderly 17,
她也十七岁
and so was she.
停！我不愿意听你的故事
Stop, I'm not interested.
我一般不跟人说心里话
I don't confess to just anyone.
这都到嘴边了，你不能让我咽回去吧
I've to continue now that I started.
咽回去吧
Take it back!
因为你说出来也是假的
It's all made up anyway.
你是个骗子
You're a conman!
北国我不知道
In our part of China,
在我南国，这样的珍藏版地雷
There are only two such landmines.
只有两颗
Both limited edition.
了然，我是假麻子！
No problem, sir. I'm a fake.
老爷给我多少那是对我的恩赐
I'll take whatever you can spare.
那么，什么时候炸？
When do you want it to blow up?
什么时候炸那是第三步
That's our denouement!
且让我把第二步慢慢走好
Let's play out our second act slowly.
都别动！
Hold still!
让她说！
Let her speak.
老二不辞而别
Two left without saying goodbye.
你出钱，我剿匪！
why not fund my expedition instead.
好啊！
Done deal!
三天之后，一定给县长一个惊喜
You shall receive a nice surprise in 3 days.
汤师爷，他是胡万的恩人
He was Hu Wan's boss.
我为什么要把人埋在衙门里
They weren't buried at the magistracy.
美国制造，一九一零
Made in U.S.A. - 1910!
呼！一响，它就没了
Bang and everything's in smithereens!
所以，不带走几条人命
So if it doesn't take some lives with it,
那就是卑鄙的浪费！
it'd be such a waste.
那么…
Well...
另外一颗地雷呢？
where's the other one?
炸了！
It exploded.
炸了？
Really?
辛亥革命的第一响
The first bang during the 1911 Revolution!
我知道了
Oh yes, I've heard!
炸在辛亥这个地方了
It went off at Xinhai!
辛亥不是个地方，是一种革命
Xinhai's not a place! It's a revolutionary icon!
您要早这么说我就了然了
You should've said so earlier.
那还是说说这颗吧
Now, tell me about this one.
谁让你问那颗的？
You must stay focused.
所以，它要炸得惊天
I want it to shake the world,
什么？
What?
这是什么狗屁道理？
What kind of stupid logic is that?
好人就得让人拿枪指着？
You threaten me because I'm good?
花姐，大哥说得对！
Flora, Chief is right!
回来！坐下！
Go back! Sit down!
你们这群王八蛋
You bunch of idiots!
我让你们把钱发给穷人
I told you to give money to the poor.
你们发给一个女人？
And you gave it to her?
我说什么来着？没人听啊！
I warned you but nobody listened.
闭嘴！天生的老骗子！
Shut up! You're a born cheat!
时时刻刻想骗我！
Always plotting to swindle me.
跟黄四郎勾勾搭搭！
Working with Huang behind my back.
一个土匪碰见一个恶霸
When a bandit confronts a godfather,
多么简单的事！
the outcome should be simple.
让你们给弄成这么烂七八糟的
How can you screw up so badly?
狸猫变太子，嘎登变出一胡万来
Abracadabra, and Hu Wan magically appeared!
可是我有一事不明
But I really didn't get it.
六具尸体
Those six bodies,
这么长的距离，那么短的时间
such a distance, so little time,
还抹着红脸蛋，你们是怎么搬来的？
how did you move them so quickly?
我跟黄四郎可是一路小跑过来的
Huang and I took the shortcut.
你们搬着六个人
You've to carry six bodies.
来不及呀！
How did you manage?
好名字！
A fine name!
充州牧，豫州牧
It has auspicious meanings.
牧之，令尊是望子成大器
You father must have high hopes.
从讲武堂出来
After graduating from military academy,
我追随过松坡将军
I enlisted in General Cai's army.
给他做过手枪队长
Served as captain of his riflemen.
那年你多大？
How old were you then?
十七
Seventeen.
少年得志啊
A youthful genius!
后来庐州会战，将军负了伤
Cai was wounded during the Battle of Luzhou,
再后来，将军死在了日本
and later died in exile in Japan.
不敢拿枪，当不了麻匪
If I don't dare to draw a gun on you,
我敢拿枪指着你
I'll never make a good bandit.
我胆儿大吧
I dare you all!
你们谁给她出的这个主意？
Whose quirky idea is this?
谁？
Whose?
我就是跟她说着玩的
I was just teasing her.
你是想当麻匪？
You want to become one of us?
对呀！我想跟你们一块儿发钱
Yes, to give money out to the poor,
把钱袋子扔到窗户里，听他们笑
to hear and share their joy.
你现在就是了
You're now one of us.
我还没准备好呢
But I am not prepared.
不用准备
No need!
你们都准备过吗？
Did you make preparation?
没有
No.
你准备过吗？
How about you?
没有啊，我吃着火锅唱着歌
I was eating hotpot and singing songs.
扑通一下掉水里，出来就到这儿了
My train plunged and I ended up here.
我们要离开鹅城
We're leaving Goose Town soon.
你就留在鹅城
But you have to stay.
不！
No.
当麻匪要听命令
A bandit must have discipline.
大哥说得对
Chief is right.
刚才说的也对
But she has a point, too.
我有个很重要的事交给你
I have an important mission for you.
我看你挺合适
I think you can manage.
这就是惊喜！
This is our nice surprise!
果然是个惊京喜
A nice surprise indeed.
果然他不姓马！
He is not Ma!
有了这个惊喜
Now that we know,
我的第二步就能走的更加悠然
My next move can be more leisurely.
悠然？
Leisurely?
盗官欺爵，放在前清
Impersonating a governor warrants capital punishment.
还要动地，还要泣鬼神
I want it to rock and roll!
了然
Understood.
选个好地方
Pick a good spot,
选个好时辰
find an auspicious time...
那么…炸谁？
So, who's our target?
你应该问…
You should've asked...
炸在哪
"Where"?
炸在哪？
Where, then?
剿匪的路上
Where the expedition force must pass.
这么快又要剿匪了？
Yet another expedition?
那这回我能多分点吧
Can I have a bigger cut this time?
你要是真的张麻子，钱都给你
You can have it all if you're the real Pocky!
你是被黄四郎买来的
You were bought by Huang?
对
Yes.
他打过你吗？ 打过
- Been mistreated? - Yes.
我打过你么？ 没有
- Have I ever laid hands on you? - No.
你恨他吗？ 恨
- Hate him? - Yes.
恨我吗？ 不恨
- And me? - No.
那你不拿枪指着他！你拿枪指着我？
Then why threaten me with a gun?
“大哥有令，散开，别开枪”
"Hold your fire. Scatter!"
“往山顶上跑，抓住他们的头儿”
"Run for the peak. Grab their leader."
西边十个
10 to the west.
南面六个
6 to the south.
我还要好好地耍耍这两只猴！
I want to toy with these circus monkeys.
我的老爷
But Master,
这两只猴子不值得您耍！
they're not worth your while.
要耍！一定要耍！
No, I must toy with them!
不耍猴，我怎么赚到两大家族的钱？
Otherwise, I couldn't get others to pay,
不耍猴，他们怎么心甘情愿地去剿匪？
the Governor couldn't go and fight the bandits,
不剿匪，他们怎么能踩到地雷呢？
and they wouldn't trot on my landmine!
黄四郎有个替身
Huang has a double.
跟他长得一模一样
They are indistinguishable.
我弄不清楚他是黄四郎，还是他替身
I can't tell if this is really Huang.
你帮我去看看
I need you to check for me.
假的！
He's a fake.
他不是黄四郎
He's not Huang.
我已经跟你们说过我不是他
Told you I'm not Huang!
我真的不是他
I really am not him.
肯定不是
I'm certain.
放了我吧，放了我
Let me go.
那好，你帮我们看住他
Keep an eye on him until our return.
等我们回来，就用你手里的枪
If you have to, use your guns.
黄老爷见笑，马某走南闯北
I've travelled all over China,
在九个地方做过县长
I have been governor in 9 counties.
靠的就是以假乱真、鱼目混珠之章法
I excel in confusing facts with fiction!
那么…马县长…
So, Governor Ma...
你说
Yes?
叫我呐！
He's addressing me.
黄老爷继续
You were saying?
我刚摸清你们的底细
Just as I uncover the truth,
你们就不打自招
you blow your own cover!
太巧了吧？
What a coincidence.
有道是，展颜消宿怨
"Stop frowning to dispel ill feelings,
一笑泯恩仇啊
and brush aside quarrels with a smile."
你想跟我和解？
Want to make peace?
好啊！我的替身呢？
Splendid. Where's my double?
还给我，前面的账一笔勾销
Return him and we'll call it quits.
撕票了
We've killed him.
哪个王八蛋让你撕票的？
Which asshole ordered his execution?
你个王八蛋让我撕票的！
You're that asshole!
开枪，你开枪我也能先打死你
I dare you to pull your trigger!
放下！
Lay down your guns!
开枪！你先开枪，我也能先打死你
I know I could take you out first.
把枪放下！我数三下
Put down your guns on my count of three!
一！二！三！
One, two, three!
老黄，你先放下
Huang, put it down!
他不懂事儿，你也不懂事啊？
He may be a brute, but you too?
老三又要走了
Now Three is leaving too.
我们活活的被你们拆散了！
You are tearing us apart!
女侠，你是为了老二还是为老三啊？
You're doing this for Two or Three?
闭嘴！
Shut up!
你左手的意思我懂
I know your left hand's intention,
右手的意思我也懂
I know your right hand's intention.
两只手这么待着，我看不懂
But both hands together...I don't get it.
要么成，要么死
I'd rather be dead!
AB型！
Typical Scorpian!
闭嘴！
Shut up!
你们都坐下
Sit down, all of you.
我再跟她聊聊
Let me talk to her.
你还敢拿枪指着我？
How dare you still point your gun at me?
满门抄斩
His whole clan dies with him!
老爷，你等着
Master, just you wait.
我这就一枪崩了他！
I'll go and blow him away!
不！
No!
他们死以前
Before they die,
死了吧？
Is he dead?
我弄死你妈的呀！
Goddamned it!
出不了城，剿不了匪
We can't fight without leaving!
黄老爷，您说话不算数啊！
You've failed to live up to your promise.
鸿门宴上说得好
You had agreed to
你带头出钱
Iead the contribution
再套出两大家族的钱来
in order to make the others pay.
可是你不但不出钱
Not only have you not put up any money,
还扮成麻匪跟我们打来打去，不仗义啊
you've also fought us posing as bandits!
错！你们看见的麻匪，是我扮的
Wrong! You saw my men dressed up as bandits.
我看见的麻匪，是你们扮的
I saw yours posing as bandits, too.
可是他们看见的麻匪
But when the others see these bandits,
他们以为是真的！
they wouldn't know that they're fakes.
现在正是让他们出钱剿匪的好时机！
Now is the time to pay for the expedition.
只要我出钱，他们一定会出
If I pay, others will follow suit.
你的钱呢？
Where's your money?
早已经为你准备好了
It's all here.
鹅城到处都是我的钱
I've money stowed away everywhere!
都在这儿？
It's all here?
这只是一半
This is only half of my share.
我们想赚多少，他们必须出多少
Each family will have to put up the same.
三舅，有诈！
Uncle, this is a trap.
诈？
A trap?
来回这么多趟，死了这么多人
After all these confrontations,
他一分钱都不出
he has not put up a dime.
今天怎么突然出了这么多钱？
Why so generous all of a sudden?
你觉得突然？
Did I surprise you?
太突然了
Yes, you did.
我也觉得突然
I surprised myself too!
想知道吗？
Want to know why?
过来
Come here.
我要当…
I - want - to - be -
县长
Governor!
你？
You?
我做不了县长？
I won't make a Governor?
我不像个县长？
Don't I look the part?
像！我们一走，你就上任鹅城
Yes, you can swear in as soon as we leave.
鹅城？
Goose Town?
我买了六个县的县长！
I bought governorship of 6 more counties!
我一个人当不过来
I can't handle all on my own!
所以…
That is why...
出去
Get out!
退下
Leave us.
老马，你来帮我当三个县的县长
I need you to govern three of them for me.
好啊！这事我拿手
Brilliant! I'm good at governing.
等会！
Hey, wait...
那…那我干什么呀？
What about me, then?
你嘛…
You...
来当一个假的张麻子！
can play "Pocky" Zhang!
好啊
Great idea!
自宣统皇帝退位以后
Since the abdication of the last Emperor,
鹅城一共来过51任县长
Goose Town has 51 governors.
他们都是王八蛋、禽兽、畜生、寄生虫
They're all bastards, parasites and leeches!
但是这位马邦德县长
But our beloved Governor Ma,
他不是王八蛋，不是畜生
is neither a bastard, parasite,
不是禽兽，也不是寄生虫
Ieech, nor a beast!
张麻子一来，你我可就没命了
We're doomed if we run into him!
张麻子！…
Speak of the devil!
告诉弟兄们，散开
Tell our men to hold their fire!
别开枪，往山顶上跑
Scatter! Run for the peak.
我不会用枪
I've never used a gun.
老三，你教教她
Three, show her how.
这照片是你吗？
Is that your photo?
是我！
Yes, it's mine.
是吗？
Sure?
是
Yes,
那时候我还很瘦
I was slimmer then.
这就不是你
I don't think it's you.
你说他不是我？
It isn't?
不是！
No, it isn't.
我说他也不是我！
I don't think so either.
这根本就不是我！
No, that ain't me.
那到底是怎么回事？
What is this all about?
我还想知道是怎么回事
I was totally baffled myself.
花钱买了个县官，我总得有个证件吧
When I bought the post, I needed papers.
我去照相馆照相，取照片的时候
I had my picture taken at a gallery,
他们给我的就是这张
and that's what they gave me.
我说这不是我，他们说这就是你
I said the man in the photo wasn't me.
我说他不是我！他们说这就是你
They insisted that it was.
没办法，我就把它贴在这了
I've no choice but to use it.
哦！是这样！
Is that so?
哦什么呀？
Bullshit!
这明明是我！
That's obviously me!
我才是马邦德！
I am the real Ma Bangde.
哦！是这样
Is that so?
是这样！我进城以前遇见麻匪
I was ambushed by bandits on my way here.
幸亏有他，才躲过一劫
He saved my life.
我一想，索性让他假扮县长
So I let him take the post.
毕竟是自家外甥嘛
After all, he's my nephew.
三舅，这话能跟他说吗？
Uncle, we shouldn't be telling him this.
闭嘴！
Shut up!
出了城，吃着火锅，还唱着歌
singing, eating hot pot and be merry,
突然就被麻匪劫了！
when bandits jump on you from nowhere!
所以，没有麻匪的日子
I long for a world without thieves,
才是好日子！
for days of wine and roses!
县长，请！
Governor, please!
出发！
March!
恩人
Saviour,
给你看个宝贝
want to check this out?
这不就是委任状嘛
Isn't that the warrant?
念念，念念
Read it out loud.
兹委任马邦德…怎么了？
Ma Bangde is hereby appointed...
后面！
Read on!
中华民国八年八月…
8th month of the 8th year of the Republic...
念你没念过的字，当中！
Don't miss out the words in between...
兹委任马邦德为康城县长…
Ma Bangde is hereby appointed Kang County governor...
等会…
Hang on...
康城？
Kang County?
不是鹅城吗？
Not Goose Town?
从来都是康城
It has always been Kang County.
好小子
You bastard!
怨你啊
Blame yourself!
你把我泡水里，九筒扣脸上
When you dumped me in the river,
闹钟咔咔咔响，吓死我了！
scared as I was, I had an inspired moment.
我灵机一动，让你去鹅城
I brought you to Goose Town.
这鹅城和康城有什么不一样啊？
What's their difference?
康城富饶，鹅城凶险
Kang County is affluent. Goose Town is deadly.
那你为什么让我去啊？
Why Goose Town for me?
你鬼扯叹，截火车！
You're a tough cookie, aren't you?
告诉你啊，你进了鹅城就有两种情况
There can only be two outcomes.
第一，你进城就被黄四郎弄死
Either Huang kills you dead,
告诉弟兄们，上东边去
Tell everyone to go east.
抓着活的，问出他们头在哪
Bring one in for interrogation.
我亲手宰了他！
I'll kill their leader myself.
上东边
Let's move.
头在哪儿？
Where's your leader?
北面，脸上有麻子的就是
In the north, with a pockmarked face.
北面！山顶上
Go north! On the hill.
我没死吧？
Am I dead?
没有！没死！
No, you're still alive.
没死！要说什么？我帮你吹
Do you want to signal a message?
怎么吹？怎么吹？
How do you whistle?
你带我走吧！
Can you lead the way?
不…跑不动！…
No, I can't run any more.
我带你走
Follow me, then.
跑不动…！
I can't run.
不是嘴坏了吗？
You've only blown up your cheeks.
嘴坏了用脚跑啊！
Your legs are fine.
“大哥死了，大哥死了”
"Chief is dead! Chief is dead!"
大哥死了？
The Chief is dead?
你把大哥给吹死了
You just signalled the Chief's death!
老五，你去看看
Five, go check it out.
大哥
Chief!
他们说你死了！
They said you're dead.
放他妈的屁！我这不还活着吗？
Bullshit! Am I not alive?
“大哥没死”
"Chief is alive and well!"
放他妈的屁怎么没吹啊？
Why missed out signalling "bullshit"?
“放你妈的屁”
"You're full of shit!"
听见没
Hear that?
骂咱们放你娘的屁呢！
He said we're full of shit.
等会儿
Wait.
你最不懂事！
You're the worst!
你们什么时候出城剿匪？
When are you leaving for your expedition?
走不了
We aren't.
钱不到手，出不了城
We can't leave without funding.
枪在手，跟我走！
Those with guns follow me.
杀四郎，抢碉楼！
Kill Huang and storm his citadel...
枪在手，跟我走！
Those with guns follow me.
杀四郎，抢碉楼！
Kill Huang and storm his citadel...
枪在手，跟我走！
Those with guns follow me.
杀四郎，抢碉楼！
Kill Huang and storm his citadel...
枪在手，跟我走！
Those with guns follow me.
去看看
Go and take a look.
要出人命啦！
Someone will die!
东边…
East...
你到底是不是张麻子？
Are you really "Pocky" Zhang?
我是
Yes, I am.
我可是快要死的人了
I am about to kick the bucket,
别骗我
don't lie to me.
放心
Don't worry.
我就是张麻子
I really am "Pocky" Zhang.
麻子
Pocky!
屁股…
My ass...
屁股疼
it hurts.
师爷
Counselor.
屁股在树上呢
Your ass is on that tree.
不疼了
You can't feel it.
我树上的屁股的口袋里
On my ass over there,
有五张委任状
I have another five warrants.
都给你
Take them.
听我的，千万别回鹅城
Promise never to return to Goose Town.
你呀，弄不过黄四郎
You can't beat Huang.
带上银子，走吧
Take the money and run.
你放心，我不回鹅城
Don't worry, I won't go back.
其实，我还有两档子事儿骗过你
I lied about two other things.
骗了就骗了吧
No big deal.
不行
No.
我死之前，我必须告诉你
I must confess before I die.
你说，头一档子
What was the first lie, then?
我…我能说这第二档子事儿吗？
Can I confess my second lie first?
好
Yes.
那谁…你还记得吗？
Do you still remember...
咱们一个字，斩！
We simply want them...dead!
可他说过
He has sworn publicly,
三天之后斩我人头
to behead me in 3 days.
荆柯当年还说要斩秦始皇呢
Some said I'd win the lottery too!
大哥，三天
Can the four of us
就我们四个要杀黄四郎？
kill Huang in three days?
对
Yes.
还把话说出去了
We've been telling everyone that.
话不说出去，事就办不成
We can't back out now!
胜算有几成啊？
What are our chances?
“三成”
"30%"
三成不是玩命吗？
30%? Are we out of our mind?
我去睡会儿啊，你们在这盯着
Time for a nap. Keep watch.
南风
Queen!
北风
Knave!
胡啦
Bingo!
大哥，银子都没了！
Chief, the money is gone.
我看见了
I could see that.
现在有四成了吧
We must have a 40% chance now!
五成？
50%?
七成？
70%?
不能吧
Surely not!
老百姓把钱都拿回家了，还三成啊？
Still only 30% after they took the money?
银子要是这么被拿走了
If things are that simple,
那钱就白发了
our efforts will be in vain.
出车！
Send the carriages!
我要你看一看，什么叫做草船借箭
I'll show you how to "borrow arrows with a straw boat"!
他今天亲自带队，出兵剿匪
He risks his life to combat the bandits.
他是我们的大英雄
He is our hero!
师爷，请！
Counselor, please.
大风起兮云飞扬
It's time for heroes to take centre stage!
安得猛士兮走四方
It's time for heroes to show their mettle!
麻匪，任何时候都要剿
We must rid ourselves of these bandits.
不剿不行
We don't have a choice.
你们想想，你带着老婆
Imagine, if you take your wife out,
我马走康城，从容上任
and I'll move on to Kang County.
第二，你有种，咱俩办了黄四郎
Or we sort out Huang instead,
就像现在这样
Iike what's happening now.
好！说得好，马邦德
Very clever!
你这个骗子
You goddamned crook!
早晚有一天你会被张麻子
One day Pocky will get you,
一枪崩了
and blast you to hell!
你崩了我？
You won't.
你舍不得
You love me too much.
你还真相信我就是张麻子？
You still think I'm "Pocky" Zhang?
你要不是张麻子，这山上可就有真麻子
If not, the real one must be somewhere around.
告诉他们
Tell them!
让老三去找老四，把南边干掉
Three joins Four to secure our south.
老七回来保护师爷！
Seven back to protect the Counselor.
“老三去找老四，干掉南面”
"Three and Four to secure the south."
“老七回来保护师爷”
"Seven back to guard the Counselor."
“我被包围了”
"I'm out-flanked."
“听我口令，甩斗笠”
"Throw the hats on my signal!"
“东边归我，西边归你”
"I'll take the east. You the west."
大哥，老三老四他们得手了
Three and Four are done.
大哥我到了！大哥我到了！
I'm back. I'm back.
师爷交给你了，快！
Stay with the Counselor!
明白！
Understood.
师爷，快！
Counselor, come!
三哥！
Three!
好像是二哥
It looks like Two.
南国张麻子在此
Pocky Zhang is here.
钱留下，银子也留下… 是二哥
- Leave your money... - It's Two.
老爷，散不了吧！
The money is not being taken!
你瞧，除了鹅，没有活物敢过去
No one dare to go near except those geese!
我去找花姐
I'll go and find Flora!
你把花姐和替身都给我找回来
Bring her and Huang's double back.
三天之内必须找回来！
We only have three days.
这个张麻子到底要干嘛呢？
What is on his mind?
他们干什么都是白干！
They're a bunch of clowns!
老爷，咱们放的是马，不是船
But we just sent horses, not straw boats.
你这个傻瓜
Idiot!
这叫比喻！比喻！…
It's only a metaphor!
不就是赤壁嘛！
You're almost metaphysical!
银子都被黄四郎收走了
Huang has taken all the silvers.
胜算都不到一成了
We've no chance of winning.
“六成”
"60%"
黄四郎都没出面啊
Huang didn't even have to show up,
老百姓把所有钱都交出去了
everyone has surrendered their money.
哪来六啊？
How can it be 60%?
说得对！
Well said!
为什么？
So why 60%?
怕啊！
It's because of fear.
怕里边有什么？
What lies beneath fear?
有怒！
Rage!
我一定把他们心里的怒给勾出来
We need to bring forth their rage!
满街枪弹在你手！
As guns and ammos wait for you,
十成白银在碉楼！
Huang hoards fortune in his citadel.
满街枪弹在你手！
As guns and ammos wait for you,
十成白银在碉楼！
Huang hoards fortune in his citadel.
屡败还屡战！
Never-say-die!
我喜欢！
I like that!
那是枪啊！要不，放马？
Those are guns! Send carriages?
拿银子，是贪！拿枪，是反
Money incites greed. But guns are seditious!
他们没这个胆！
They wouldn't dare.
银子被收走了，枪也没人拿
The money's gone, but the guns remain!
怎么办，大哥？
What do we do now?
胜算几成？
What are our chances?
“七成”
"70%"
黄四郎把所有的钱都给收了
Huang has taken all the money.
我们发的枪也没人拿
But no one takes our guns.
哪来的七成啊？
How come it's 70%?
黄四郎要是不收银子，我发枪干什么？
If he hadn't taken the money, I wouldn't have to distribute the guns!
黄四郎不收银子，我发枪干什么？
...wouldn't have distributed the guns!
我…
I...
去睡会儿
need a nap.
东风
King!
南风 胡了
- Queen! - Bingo!
我明白了
I got it!
你发的不是枪，你发的就是怒！
You were inciting rage and anger!
收枪
Collect the guns.
没动静啊
You missed?
要出人命了！
There will be fatalities!
至少得死一个
At least one of them will die!
起！
Hoist!
弟兄们，我们打赢了，凯旋
Brothers! We've won the war!
明白吗？
Understood?
明白！
Understood!
东边还有一大片！
Another group to the east.
让老七去找老三
Tell Seven to join Three!
先把西边的收拾掉
Secure our west flank.
“老七去找老三，干掉西面”
"Seven and Three to secure west flank!"
“我到了”
"I'm there!"
“不是十个，是十一个”
"There are 11 of them, not 10!"
“没事，你四，我七”
"No sweat, let's share them!"
“落停”
"Done!"
老三来信，西边搞定
Message from Three. West is secured.
这鸡叫成电台了，我看行！
These pheasant calls really work wonder!
假麻子抓到了
They caught the fake!
你是张麻子？
You're "Pocky" Zhang?
你脸上怎么没有麻子呢？
Where are your pockmarks?
这事谁问谁死！
No one asking that question has survived.
明白了！不问了
Oops! I take it back.
我这儿有一宝贝
I've got something special.
送给你了
You can have them,
能换我一条命吧？
in exchange for my life.
那…那两个人呢？
What happened to them?
说实话能换一条命吧
If I tell you, will you spare me?
快说！
Speak!
大个的被我给锯了， 比矮个的还矮
I sawed the legs off the tall one.
矮的呢？
And the short one?
当场就被吓死了
She died of fright at the sight!
师爷！
Counselor.
师爷！师爷！
Counselor...
谁让你冒充我的？
Who's behind this scam?
黄老爷
Master Huang.
麻子哪儿来的？
Nice pockmarks!
他烫的
He burnt them.
劫了几任县官？
How many governors have you robbed?
说出来能换条命吗？
Will you spare me?
快说！
Speak!
五回！五个县长全被我给干掉了
I've killed five governors,
钱我跟黄老爷给分了
and shared the loot with Master Huang.
那是什么？
What's that?
万民伞！那五个被我干掉的县长留下的
A governor's silver umbrella.
全都给你！
Take it!
山西往哪边走啊？ 我还有四把呢
- Which way to Shanxi? - I have four more.
我知道
I know the way.
说出来能换条人命吧？
Will you spare me if I tell you?
快他妈说！
Goddamned it! Speak!
往东！往东！
To the east, to the east!
哎呀！不能往东！千万不能往东！
Come back! You mustn't go that way!
山西确实是在东边
But Shanxi really is to our east.
一刀给砍了！
by that stupid Governor!
何止是愚蠢，简直就是愚蠢
That was stupid! That was ignorant!
这公平吗？
That's not justice!
不公平！
No! It's not!
乡亲们答应吗？
Can you let this pass?
不答应！
No!
我不是他
I am not him.
我知道你是替身
I know you're his double.
替他享福！替他作恶！
But you shared his life and committed his crimes.
你就应该替他，把他没受过的罪
So you should be punished
给我受够了！
as if you were him!
跪下！ 我真的不是他
- Kneel down! - I really am not him!
跪下！跪下！…
Kneel down! Kneel!
别让我发脾气
Don't make me mad!
我数三下！
On my count of three!
一！
One!
二！
Two!
一！
One!
二！
Two!
谁？哪个欠打的？
What the...? Who's the son-of-a-bitch?
又想挨板子了是吧？
Want your ass kicked again?
大人，我讨厌吗？
Am I bothering you, sir?
如果我讨厌，我立马消失！
Say the word and I'll disappear.
如果不讨厌，我继续欺负他！
If not, I'll just carry on.
很讨厌
Go away.
大人，兄弟我就走了！
Right, we're going.
需要兄弟的时候，你吐喝一声
Just yell if you need me.
兄弟立马出现
Always at your service, sir.
告辞！告辞！走！
Goodbye, sir. Beat it!
下一步有什么打算？
What's next for you?
留在鹅城代替我？
Take my place here?
我不是家禽
I'm not a caged bird.
你是野兽
You're a predator.
进城那天，如果我亲自去接你
The day of your inauguration,
不是叫胡万过去给你捣乱
had I greeted you in person,
我弄不清楚你到底是老汤
I can't quite figure you out.
还是马邦德？
Counselor Tang or Governor Ma?
但是你没了
Now that you're gone,
张麻子也没了
"Pocky" Zhang, too, is no more.
真的也没了，假的也没了
Fact or fiction no longer matter now.
兄弟，我要帮你把这个县长当下去
For you, I'll go back and finish this war!
弟兄们
Brothers!
回鹅城！
March on Goose Town!
这个张麻子
This "Pocky" Zhang
杀了假麻子
has killed his imposter.
得了钱，不逃命
But instead of fleeing with the money,
莫非要跟我鱼死网破？
he wants a showdown with me.
那就请官兵来剿匪！
Let's get reinforcement.
我早就派胡百过去了
I've sent Hu Bai to fetch troops.
三天之后郭旅长的骑兵就到了
Cavalry will arrive in 3 days.
县长要斩黄四郎！
Governor swears to behead Huang,
谁人不想斩黄郎！
public enemy number one.
拐卖壮丁贩烟土！
Trades in opium and human misery,
杀了五任好县长！
Huang has killed five governors.
一成白银送你手！
The money that's been given out,
九成真金黄家藏！
is but one-tenth of his hoard!
邦德发誓三天内！
In memory of his dead comrades,
除暴安良祭老汤！
Ma will parade Huang's head in 3 days!
白花花的银子都散给了穷人
He gave away all his money to the poor.
作孽！
Disgraceful!
让子弹飞一会儿！
Let the bullets fly!
枪响了
Shots were fired!
看！
Look!
怒了，全都怒了！
They're all raging mad!
他妈的的刁民，敢杀我的马？
How dare they shot my horse?
枪在手，跟我走！
Those with guns follow me.
杀四郎，抢碉楼！
Kill Huang and storm his citadel...
枪在手，跟我走！
Those with guns follow me.
杀四郎，抢碉楼！
Kill Huang and storm his citadel...
枪在手，跟我走！
Those with guns follow me.
杀四郎，抢碉楼！
Kill Huang and storm his citadel...
大哥，大哥你看
Chief, look.
跟我们来的只有它们！
Only they have come this far with us!
高兴早了，没人帮咱们！
We're on our own!
明白了！
I see.
谁赢，他们帮谁！
They will only side with the victors.
黄四郎四百人，我们四个人，怎么赢啊？
We can't overcome Huang's 400 men!
打！打就能赢！
Shoot! We can win!
打哪儿？这只有铁门
What's our target? There's only a gate.
就打铁门！
Let's blast the gate, then.
他们鼓动了多少人？
How many people have they brought?
就他们四个
Just the four of them.
不可能吧！
You're kidding!
还有…
and also...
五十只鹅
fifty geese.
打！打够！
Great! Let them shoot!
让他打个够！
Let them goddamned shoot!
大哥，天快亮了
It's almost day break.
三哥不回来可就…
If Three doesn't return in time...
我知道你是怎么想的
I know what's on your mind.
知道惊叹号吧
Can you draw an exclamation mark?
在门上打出个惊叹号来
Let's do one on the gate!
好日勒
Right on.
这像惊叹号吗？那点呢？
What's that? Where's the dot?
歪了
You missed!
躲开
Move over.
勾？
A hook stroke?
再看
Look again!
问号
A question mark!
可是六子，老二，师爷、夫人
But Six, Two, Counselor and his wife...
我听不到他们的声音了
I can no longer hear their voice.
而且永远听不到了
Never ever again.
你们四个人
Their four lives,
换我五代家业
in exchange for my heirloom,
不合算吗？
isn't that enough?
怎么算帐那是你的事
That's none of my business.
对我来说…
To me,
钱是钱，人是人
they are separate issues.
钱归了你，我认了
You could have kept the money.
为什么要散给他们？
But why did you give it away?
黄老爷，我问你个问题
Master Huang, let me ask you a question.
说
Shoot!
你说是钱对我重要
Which is more important to me?
还是你对我重要？
You or your fortune?
我
Me.
再想想
Think again.
不会是钱吧？
Can it be the money?
再想想
Think again.
还是我重要
I still think it's me.
你和钱对我都不重要
Neither matters to me.
那谁重要？
Then what is?
没有你，对我很重要
To rid of you is more important.
你不是找火柴吧？
Looking for a light?
不是
No.
那…
You must be...
你是找这个
Iooking for this.
你是个体面人
You're a man of honour.
只有一颗子弹
There's only one bullet left.
够
That's enough.
等等
Wait.
有话要我带给老汤？
Any message for Tang?
对了，告诉他…
Right, tell him...
我对不起他
I owe him an apology.
我骗了他
I lied to him.
你骗了他什么？
What was your lie?
我跟他说不回鹅城了
I said I wouldn't come back.
可是我回来了
But here I am.
你…
You...
你应该说到做到
You should have kept your promise.
是，我对不起他
Yes, I let him down.
可是我对你
But when it comes to you,
就要说到做到
I'll definitely keep my words.
明白
Understood.
明白！
Understood...
县长，县长…
Governor...
这两把椅子归我了
These chairs are mine.
大哥…
Chief...
别慌
Easy...
我能问你个问题吗？
Can I ask you a question?
说
Sure.
你喜欢花姐对吗？
You fancy Flora, right?
县长，县长
Governor,
我觉得我可以出现了
may I interrupt?
刚才我都听见了
I overheard everything.
他可不是个体面的人
Huang is not an honourable man.
上海就是浦东！
Shanghai is Pudong!
浦东就是上海！
Pudong is Shanghai!
小子，你只要打得准
If you can shoot straight,
什么时候都能跑！
you'll have nothing to worry!
把你们的子弹
Empty your guns
从那问号的点里打过去
at the question mark!
好啦！快！
Okay!
大哥…！
Chief, chief...
说，说话
Speak up!
我回来了
I'm back!
三天整！
Three days,
就这事
one mission!
人呢？
Where are they?
都在那
They're here.
你可回来了！
You're back, at last.
我不是他，我只是个唱戏的！
I'm not Huang! I'm just an actor!
怎么回事？
What happened?
他跑我就追，他跑我就追
He ran away and I chased after him.
就越跑越远了！
We ran a long way!
他跑我就堵
I caught up with them.
他跑我就堵，就给堵回来了！
He finally succumbed after I'd him cornered.
就这么简单？
That was it?
对，就这么简单
Yes, that simple.
弟兄们
Brothers!
为了庆贺三哥回来
To mark Three's return,
把所有的子弹都打出去
Iet's go and empty our guns!
好！ 走！
- Right. - Let's go!
那我呢？
What about me?
趴下！
Squat!
就他们四个人？
Just four of them?
留不留啊？
Let him go?
欠打的过来！过去！…
You bastard, go over here! Over there!
站好了！
Stand properly!
乡亲们！
My fellow townsfolk!
黄四郎是死了
Huang has died!
但死得太便宜了
But he has got off lightly!
咔嚓呀
Swoosh!
被那个愚蠢县长
He was fell in one blow
我给了他一把手枪
I gave him a pistol.
他要是体面，你就让他体面
He can take his own life.
他要是不体面，你就帮他体面
If he doesn't, lend him a hand.
我明白！
Understood.
我有九种办法弄死他！
I have 9 ways to skin this cat!
九种！
Nine ways!
听我的雷声！
You'll hear my roar!
是有这么回事，怎么了？
Maybe just a little. Why?
千万别说是我说的
Don't say I tipped you off.
大哥，我们准备去上海了
Chief, we're off to Shanghai.
不跟我回山里了？
Not riding back with me?
说一遍！
Say it out loud!
赢了！凯旋！
Yes, victory.
招摇过市！
Let's parade him.
跟我走！
Follow me.
黄四郎被抓了！
Huang's been captured.
Huang's been captured!
黄四郎被抓了！
Huang's been captured.
杀！
Kill!
糟了，糟了！
Shit, we're in trouble!
我成替身了
I've died as my double!
去碉楼，拿回你们自己的东西
Reclaim what's yours from the citadel!
跟我来！
Come with me!
杀！
Charge!
杀…！
跟我来！
Follow me!
碉楼打进去了？
The citadel's been breached?
对！
Yes!
黄四郎被抓住了
Huang's been captured!
对！
Yes!
正被当成替身，挨揍呢
They took him for his double.
黄四郎的威风是被你砍了
You've ended Huang's reign.
他这肉身怎么办啊？
What do we do with him now?
结果会不会不一样？
would things have turned out differently?
那帽子挺好，我喜欢
It was a nice hat. I liked it.
那不是最好的，我家里还有更好的
I have nicer ones at home.
转头送给你
I can give them to you.
一下子弄成了这样
Everything's gone in a flash.
你让我输得很惨啊！
You've totally wiped me out.
惨吗？黄老爷
It's not that bad.
你现在还抽着烟
You're still having a smoke,
还说着话
still chit-chatting.
还想回山里啊？
Still want to resume banditry?
您这腿脚都不利落了
You're too old for this.
怎么也不跟我打个招呼
You should've given me a heads-up.
这不正要跟您打招呼了嘛
That's what we're doing!
你不是要跟我当麻匪，到处发钱吗？
Didn't you want to be one of us?
今天不是把钱都发光了吗？
I just helped to dish out the money.
还有比今天更过瘾的？
I've never had a more satisfying day!
你看我都穿上这身了！
I'm even dressed for the part!
这么说…
So...
你改主意了？
you've changed your mind?
那还用说吗
That goes without saying!
老三，你有什么打算？
What's your plan, Three?
我要替二哥娶她
I'm going to marry her, on behalf of Two.
老二啊老二…
Two...
大哥，我是老三
Chief, I'm Three!
老三，你跟我在一起
Three, it no longer thrills you
不高兴吗？ 高兴
- to ride with me? - Yes!
就是…
But...
有点不轻松
it's been hard going lately.
你们俩呢？ 有点
- What about you? - We've had...
不轻松
better days.
老七呢？
Seven?
大哥…
Chief...
姑娘
Flora,
你这么拿着枪
hold your guns like this,
更好看
makes you look even cooler.
送你了
They're yours.
大哥，那我们先走一步啊！
Chief, we've got to go.
走了，大哥
Goodbye, Chief.
走！
Go!
走了，大哥
Bye, Chief!
别忘了下回跟我打个招呼啊
Give me a heads-up next time.
易守难攻，万夫莫开！
It is simply impregnable.
县长英雄气概，师爷文采斐然
An intrepid governor, an erudite counselor.
珠联璧合！二位请！
What a dream team!
六爷的死，壮烈！
Master Six has died heroically.
今天请县长来
I've invited you here today
就是要当面为六爷讨回这个公道！
to witness how justice is done.
如果真的是黄某指使
If I'm proven to be the instigator,
那我就像六爷一样
I will follow Master Six's footstep,
当众剖腹自杀！
and disembowel myself!
不但自杀，还请县长您
I invite you to be my second,
老大往往是空架子
It is hard to be a boss.
每天眼一睁，几百人吃、喝、拉、撒
Hundreds of people everyday
都要等着我伺候
waiting to be fed.
真正落到我嘴里的，能有几口
There is little left for me.
如果县长真的急着赚钱
If you're looking to make a fast buck,
我倒是有个好去处！
I know exactly what to do.
哦？请讲！
Please tell.
张麻子
Pocky Zhang!
真死了！
One of them just died!
张麻子？
Pocky Zhang?
对，张麻子！
Yes, Pocky Zhang!
那么这个张麻子，是跟我们有关系呢？
What has he got to do with us?
还是跟钱有关系？
Or with our money?
都有关系！
Everything!
莫非他在鹅城？
Is he here in Goose Town?
在…
Well, yes...
也不在！
and no!
黄老爷这话，还挺有玄机啊！
Master Huang speaks in riddles!
六爷，挺住！我去给你请大夫！
Hang in there! I'll get a doctor!
别走！是不是只有一碗！
There's only one bowl, right?
是不是只有一碗！是不是！
该你了
Your turn!
我知道你只吃了一碗
I knew it all along.
你上当了
You fell for it.
不能杀…！我不能放！
You mustn't kill him! No, I won't!
为什么不能杀？
Tell me why I should spare him,
说不出说法来，我把你一起杀了
or I'll shoot you, too.
我
No, it's "me"!
你？
You?
你，你自己
You, you yourself!
我自己，我自己
Yes, me and me alone.
听不见
I can't hear you.
只给了一碗的钱
and paid only for one.
放屁，我就吃了一碗的粉
Bullshit! I have only eaten one bowl!
给了他一碗的钱！
And I paid him for one.
他吃了几碗？
How many bowls did he eat?
两碗
Two...
不可能！
No way!
六爷是县长的儿子
Master Six is the Governor's godson,
怎么能欠你的粉钱呢？
why would he want to cheat you?
就是吃了两碗，只给了一碗的钱
But he ate two bowls and paid for one.
县长要给我们鹅城一个公平
The Governor brings justice to our town.
好！
Good!
我今天讨的就是一个公平
And justice is what I seek today!
对
Hear hear!
问谁讨？问县长儿子。为什么？
From the Governor's son, of course.
他吃了两碗粉，只给了一碗的钱
Ate two bowls, paid for one!
这就叫作不公平！
That's so wrong!
既然县长儿子带头不公平
Since his boy is guilty of unjust,
那县长说的话就是个屁
the Governor's crusade is bullshit!
我操
Screw you!
六爷…
Master Six...
胡万，六爷是县长的儿子
Master Six is the Governor's godson!
怎么会欠他的粉钱呢？
Would he cheat over a bowl of jelly?
你亲眼看见了？
Did you see it with your own eyes?
嘿，你个吃里爬外的东西
You double-crosser!
怎么着？
What's wrong with you?
屁股不疼了？
You're thinking with your butts?
今不聊屁股的事
It's not about my butts.
就聊凉粉
We're here for the truth!
一碗就是一碗，两碗就是两碗
One or two bowls?
不能含糊
No beating about the bush!
六爷，汉子！佩服！
I admire your courage, sir.
一就是一，二就是二
I know how to count!
我今天就吃了一碗凉粉
I ate only one bowl!
你给了一碗的钱，吃了两碗粉
You ate two and paid for one.
你没钱是吧，我帮你给！
If you can't afford it, my treat!
看见了吗？多少碗我都付得起！
I can afford all the jelly in this world!
但是吃一碗的粉，就给一碗的钱
But I pay only for what I ate.
这么多钱，他吃了多少碗粉啊
How many bowls did he eat?
马某人这个县长，买来的
I bought this governorship.
买官就是为了赚钱
Sole purpose is to get rich.
而且，马某人不喜欢赚穷人的钱
But I don't take from the poor.
那你想赚谁的钱呢？
Then who are you targeting?
谁有钱就赚谁的！
Only the wealthy people.
那谁有钱？
Who are the wealthy?
你有钱
Such as you.
爽快！县长看上什么了，随便拿
Whatever you fancy, help yourself.
我不是土匪！我是县长
I'm no bandit. I'm a governor.
县长赚钱得讲究个名正言顺才是
I make my fortune the proper way.
说得好
Well said!
我们鹅城有两大家族
Goose Town has two big families.
都是把人卖到美国修铁路
They sell people to America to build railroads,
赚的都是美金
in return for dollars!
还说刀的事
What do you mean by dolls?
不是…美金是美国人用的钱
No, d-o-l-l-a-r-s! American money.
美金！懂吗？
Dollar! You know?
美金，收到了
Oh, dollars!
黄老爷一来，钱就到了
I can smell it in your presence!
喝一杯吧 好，来
- Let's drink to that! - Great, cheers!
来…
Cheers!
黄老爷，客气了
Master Huang is so modest.
整个南国谁不知道
It is an open secret that,
在鹅城
in Goose Town,
你黄四郎是老大！
Master Huang is our real boss!
明白吗？ 不明白
- Know what I mean? - No
我是做什么生意的？明白吗？
Know what I do for a living?
不明白
No.
小半个民国的烟土
Half the opium smokers in this nation
都是黄老爷您在贩卖
rely on Master Huang for their supply!
错！不过是给刘都统当跑腿的
No, I'm only a pawn for General Liu.
而且只是其中一条腿
I'm just one of his runners!
那么刘都统到底有几条腿呢？
How many runners does Liu have?
三条叹
Three.
明白！事成之后，一百八十万如数奉还
Yes, we'll pay you back $1.8 million,
咱们分两大家族那点儿钱！
and split the dollars from the others.
一百八十万不用还！
There's no need to pay him back!
不就是剿匪么！剿！
We'll hit these bandits hard!
咱们把张麻子劫走的那点钱
Whatever they seized in the past,
全拿回来，还给黄老爷！
we will retrieve for the Master.
到那个时候
Look at the bigger picture,
这一百八十万就是九牛身上的一根毛
the $1.8 million bounty is but a strand of hair.
您还在意吗？
Surely you won't mind!
不就是个小小的张麻子吗？办他！
We'll get rid of Pocky Zhang!
硬！
Cool!
硬吗？够硬！
- Cool enough? - Very cool!
硬不硬以后再说！
We can discuss that later.
我脑子里想的只有一件事
The only thing I want to do now
替黄老爷把这条腿接上！
is to fix Master's crippled leg.
一个张麻子也太嚣张了！
Pocky Zhang's such a nuisance.
欺负到黄哥头上了，不答应
He shouldn't have messed with Master Huang!
喝酒
Let's top up.
我以为，酒一口一口喝
I believe in taking our time,
路一步一步走
doing things step by step!
步子迈大了，喀！
I don't want to break my balls
容易一场空
by over-stretching!
应该先把钱分清楚
We should agree on the split first,
再说接腿的事儿
before thinking of how to fix his leg.
嘘！安静一点
Quiet, quiet...
那么彼时彼刻
So it was there and then...
,｝合如此时此刻
A bit like, here and now!
竟能如此相像
What a coincidence!
像！很像！
Exactly!
不过你比他缺了一样东西
But you're missing something.
大哥不应该听他的
Chief should have ignored Tang.
姓汤的不是个好玩意
He is a good-for-nothing!
六爷，黄四郎这招叫杀人不用刀
Huang kills without lifting a finger!
我给你爹出的招叫杀人诛心
We must retaliate by destroying his soul.
不能拼命啊！拼命还怎么赚钱！
We can't jeopardise our chance to get rich!
六子
Six...
赚钱对我算个事儿吗？
I do not care about being rich.
我不是要杀人诛心，是没想出好办法
But I must come up with a game plan
我要把黄四郎连根都拔掉
to rid of Huang once and for all
给我点时间
Give me time,
六子，爹发誓一定给你报仇！
Pop will avenge your death.
把脸收拾收拾
Show your respect!
六爷，一路走好
Have a safe journey, Six.
六爷，一路走好！
Safe travel, Six!
先打哪一张牌？
How should I play my hand?
请客、斩首、收下当狗！
Banquet, kill him or throw him to the dogs?
斩！
I'd say kill him!
错！
No!
错？
No?
请客！
Host a banquet!
鸿门宴！凶多吉少
Dinner invitation! It's a death trap!
杀人诛心，赫然奏效！
Our ploy is working!
我再送你一个字
I have another idea: delay tactics.
拉！拉得越久，赚得越多
The longer we drag this on the better!
到时候跪在这儿的就是黄四郎本人
Huang will end up kneeling here.
什么鸿门宴！
What kind of banquet is this?
这小子到底在哪呢？
Where is he, then?
听黄爷给咱们聊聊
Let Master Huang enlightens us.
此人盘踞鹅城周边交通咽喉
He has grabbed Goose Town by its balls!
你要是肚子里只有一碗粉
If there's only one,
我死！
I'll die.
要是有两碗粉，我陪六爷一起死
If he has two bowls in him, I'll die with him!
凉粉呢？
Where's the jelly?
太浅了，我看不见
Deeper! I can't see.
六爷！佩服！
Very gutsy, sir!
凉粉在肠子里，你得横着拉一下
Try sliding the blade sideway,
你们可以把我供出来嘛！
Implicate me for all you like.
不要委屈自己哦！
I couldn't care less!
马县长，我早看出，你非等闲之辈
Governor. I sense that you're special.
不敢当
I am flattered.
不过，有胆子剿匪的人
But those who waged war on the bandits,
九死一生
none has survived.
哦，何以见得？
Why not?
张麻子非同凡人
Pocky Zhang is a tough cookie.
二十年前，我们有过一面之缘
I met him once 20 years ago.
竟有如此的缘分
Isn't that fate?
那么，缘从何起呢？
How did it happen?
灯火阑珊，他蓦然回首
He stood by a lantern and turned towards me,
而我，却隐藏在灯影里
and I was standing in the shade.
一个在明处
He was well lit up,
一个在暗处
and you're in the dark!
当我的介错人
to ritualistically cut my head off
砍下我人头，高挂艳阳楼顶！
and hang it from the restaurant.
万一不是我
If I'm proven innocent,
那就是辱我名声
those who slandered me
欺骗县长
and shamed you in the process...
你们自裁
will have to kill themselves.
要么三命抵一命，要么随时告发我
It's me against these three.
我随时死
I am ready.
黄老爷，我听说自裁用短刀
You should use this for disembowelment.
长刀归介错人
The full blade is for your second.
是吗？
Really?
果然在行！县长随时可以当我的介错人
It's great to have an expert as my second!
马县长，请！
This way, please.
黄老爷还是条大腿
And Master is the most able one!
对！大腿！
Yes, the strongest one!
可是我这条腿…
But this runner,
断了！
is now crippled!
断了？
Crippled?
怎么断的？
What happened?
我的货十回有八回被张麻子劫走了！
Zhang has seized nearly all my goods.
你想想，他赚了多少钱？
Imagine what he can make from them.
那这个张麻子很富有啊！
He must be very well off!
还有这种事儿？
I wonder if this is true.
如果你们可以去剿匪的话
You can write your own cheque,
钱要多少有多少
if you can take him out!
我们没胆子剿匪
We wouldn't dare to!
但是，借剿匪之名敛财的胆子
But if this can make us rich,
还是有，而且很大！
I wouldn't mind having a go!
那就不要怪我！就怪你们没出息
Then blame yourself for your timidity!
不过，我还可以帮你们一个忙
But I would be happy to assist.
我出钱，当诱饵
I can put up money as a bait.
我出多少，两大家族必须出多少！
The families have to match my contribution.
就等您这句话呢！足够！
We're hoping you'd say that.
那您出八十万？
How about $800,000?
不！我出一百八十万
No! I'll put up $1.8 million!
出得多，赚得多！
The more the merrier!
不会是脸上的麻子吧
You mean his facial scars?
当然不是
Of course not.
那么是什么呢？
Then what is it?
你还聊钱是吧？不聊接腿？
If you want to settle the split now,
那你们俩聊吧
then just carry on.
师爷，你定
Counselor, you decide.
先聊钱吧
About the dollars,
钱到手，按照惯例，三七分
Iet's do a customary 30-70 split.
你也太不仗义了吧！
How can you even say that?
黄老爷为这事忙前忙后
Master Huang is so instrumental.
你就分人家三成？
And you give him only 30%?
怎么也得对半分啊！
Let's go 50-50!
那我…那我错了
My apologies, Master Huang.
你太错了
So inconsiderate!
师爷
Counselor,
我们还是听县长的，对半分
I'll go along with that: 50-50.
如果真有胆子剿匪
If you've the guts to take on the bandits,
两大家族的钱
the dollars from the two families,
就值一根毛
are but strands of hair!
一根毛！
Strands of hair!
哪是一根啊！
May not be even that!
胆子你是有的
I know you have the courage.
本事呢？
But ability-wise...?
我凭什么相信你能剿张麻子？
How do I know if you can overcome Zhang?
黄老爷，容兄弟问你个问题
May I ask you a question, sir?
请
Go ahead.
张麻子能劫你的货
If Zhang can seize your goods,
为什么不能进你的家呢？
why can't he break in here?
我这碉楼，固若金汤
My citadel is impregnable.
易守难攻，他进不来！
There's no way that he can get in.
那你怎么就真的相信
Are you sure
只有我跟师爷进了你的碉楼呢？
that we're the only ones here?
说让咱们撤？
An order to retreat!
撤？ 那撤么？
- Split? - You sure?
撤
Let's split.
“遵命，但我很担心你”
"Chief, watch your back."
听见了吧？
Did you hear that?
听见了
Yes.
张麻子进不来的地方，我能进来
Where Pocky fails to breach, I succeeded!
张麻子不想死的时候，我能让他死
I can kill him when he is least expecting it.
又死一个！
Another one bites the dust!
好，保重大哥
Chief, take care.
保重
Take care.
大哥再见
Goodbye, Chief!
Bye, Chief!
再见大哥
张麻子！
"Pocky" Zhang!
老六，老二，师爷，夫人
Six, Two, Counselor, Madam...
你们看到了吧
Did you see that?
老三，去上海还是浦东？
Three, Shanghai or Pudong?
老三，去浦东还是上海？
Three, Pudong or Shanghai?